<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The spirituall architecture. Or, the balance of Gods sanctuary to discerne the weigh and solidity of a true and sincere, from the leuitie, and vanitie of a false and counterfeit profession of Christianity. Wherein also the sandy foundations of the papisticall faith are briefely discouered. A sermon preached at Pauls Crosse the 16. of Nouember, 1623. by Robert Barrell, Master of Arts, and minister of Gods word at Maidstone in Kent</title>
            <author>Barrell, Robert.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 199 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 42 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04847</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1498</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120643</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855838</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855838</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21343</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04847)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21343)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 872:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The spirituall architecture. Or, the balance of Gods sanctuary to discerne the weigh and solidity of a true and sincere, from the leuitie, and vanitie of a false and counterfeit profession of Christianity. Wherein also the sandy foundations of the papisticall faith are briefely discouered. A sermon preached at Pauls Crosse the 16. of Nouember, 1623. by Robert Barrell, Master of Arts, and minister of Gods word at Maidstone in Kent</title>
                  <author>Barrell, Robert.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 68 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Augustine Matthewes, and Iohn Norton,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1624.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21343:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21343:1"/>
            <p>THE SPIRITVALL ARCHITECTVRE.</p>
            <p>OR, The Balance of Gods Sanctuary to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the weight and ſolidity of a true and ſincere, from the Leuitie, and vanitie of a falſe and counterfeit profeſsion of Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>Wherein alſo the ſandy foundations of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſticall faith are briefely diſcouered.</p>
            <p>A Sermon preached at <hi>Pauls</hi> Croſſe the 16. of Nouember, 1623. by ROBERT BARRELL, Maſter of Arts, and Miniſter of Gods word at Maidſtone in Kent.</p>
            <q>For we are labourers together with God, ye are Gods hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry, and Gods building. <bibl>1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.9.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Si audire vis &amp; non facere, adificas, ſed ruinam aedificas, &amp; ruina tua te tollit: ergo vna eſt ſecuritas, &amp; aedifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>care, &amp; ſupra Petram aedificare. <bibl>Aug. Tract. 7. in Iohannem:</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed at <hi>London</hi> by <hi>Auguſtine Matthewes,</hi> and <hi>Iohn Norton.</hi> 1624.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:21343:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21343:2"/>
            <head>TO THE MOST RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VEREND FATHER IN GOD, GEORGE BY THE di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Prouidence Arch-biſhop of Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury his Grace, Primate of all England, and Metropolitane, one of the Lords of his Maieſtes moſt Honourable Priuy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, my very ſingular good Lord.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt Reuerend Father in God;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T may bee thought too high a praeſumption (and that not altogether vniuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,) that I ſhould ſeeke to ſhroud theſe my poore Labours vnder the roofe of your <hi>Gracious Patronage:</hi> which I doe not out of any confidence of the worth of them (for alaſſe I am too conſcious to my owne wants to bee ſo arrogantly preſumptuous) but out of the Conſcience of that great obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation
<pb facs="tcp:21343:3"/> wherein I ſtand bound vnto your Grace for your Graces manifold vndeſerued fauours, whereof I humbly deſire to make this publique acknowledgement. It is a ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led caſe in the Ciuill Law, <hi>mancipato Patre mancipantur &amp; filii,</hi> the Children are inuol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with their Father in the ſame engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: and the Fruits doe of beſt right ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaine to him that is owner of the Field. To whom then ſhould this my poore Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant, and theſe fruits of my poore Labours more rightly appereain then to your Grace; vpon whom I haue ſuch an eſpeciall depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance in the Place where I liue, and to whom I moſt deſeruedly owe my ſelfe, and the beſt of my poore Seruice. Moreouer the whole Engliſh Clergy (whereof I am a poore vnworthy member) and the whole Church of England, and Cauſe of Religion owes much vnto your Grace: whereof (vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our moſt Religious, Learned and graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Soueraigne) you are a maine Pillar and Sppor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er; not onely by your vigilant eye of circumſpection, in gouerning this Church (according to your high place) but by your zealous tongue in Preaching, and learned
<pb facs="tcp:21343:3"/> Pen in writing. I write not this to flatter your Grace, for (beſides that my nature ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horres ſuch baſeneſſe) he needs no falſe and flattering praiſes, that abounds with true: and St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſaith truly; A good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence neither deſires praiſe nor feares accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Epiſt. 31. For my part, I ſhould not haue preſumed to publiſh to the world theſe my poore Labours, (which doth occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion mee humbly to craue your Graces Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage) but that in theſe dayes, wherein ſo many <hi>Babiloniſh Tobiahs and Sanballats,</hi> ſeeke by all meanes to hinder, and (if they could) to ruine it, euery true hearted Iſraelite that can lay but one ſtone to further the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Gods Temple, &amp; the walls of his Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, muſt not ſit idle. Seing therefore your Grace is heerein a Maiſter-builder; vouchſafe (I beſeech you) your gracious ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of this little Stone that I haue hewen to lay in this Building: and your Noble Patronage of me and my poore La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, though the meaneſt of thoſe that ſerue at Gods Altar: (for euen the Sunne in the Firmament ſhines aſwell on the low Shrub as the tall Cedar, and ſends his bright
<pb facs="tcp:21343:4"/> and glorious beames, aſwell into the poore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans Cottage, as the Noble-mans Pallace) which if your Grace ſhall vouchſafe to doe, you ſhal therby encourage me (to the vtmoſt of my poore power and skill) to bee ſtill hewing more Stones for this Building; and binde me euer, as already you haue done, to be a dayly Suitor, and earneſt Solicitor, to the higheſt Throne of grace and mercy, that the confluence of all wiſhed temporall bleſsings and ſpirituall graces, may be pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red downe vpon your Graces head moſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly in this Life; with the euerlaſting addition of a Crowne of Glory in the Life to come.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Graces moſt bounden and deuoted Seruant. <hi>ROBERT BARRELL.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:21343:4"/>
            <head>The Authours Preface to the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous and charitable Reader; not ſo much the importunity of my friends, (though I haue been much ſolicited therevnto) hath cauſed me to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh this Sermon to the view of the world, as that Eye which I had therein to Gods glory and thy good: for being preſſed by ſome of my eſpeciall friends to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh it as a Sermon, which in theſe dayes, of too much tottering inconſtancie in Religion, might be ſome ſtay to wauering and vnſtable ſoules, and ſo doe ſome good in the Church of God: I thought my ſelfe moſt vnworthy to receiue a mite, (much leſſe a talent) from the Lord, if I ſhould not moſt willingly and cheerefully caſt it into Gods treaſurie: for although of late, many other worthies of our Iſrael haue<note n="a" place="margin">Luc. 21.1 &amp;c</note> out of the ſuperfluity and abundant riches of their knowledge, caſt in much more: yet I hope this mite (which I haue caſt in with as good an inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as any, though much more able than my ſelfe to doe good in the Church of God, (will be accepted of him who loues a cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full giuer, and whither it be little or much)<note n="b" place="margin">2. Cor. 8.12.</note> accepts the gift according to the ability which himſelfe hath giuen. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaith: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Let all things be done to aedification: 1.</hi> Cor. <hi>14.26.</hi> My ſcope therefore in this ſermon is to teach thee the art of <hi>Spirituall Architecture:</hi> that is, how to build vp thy ſelfe to be an houſe or temple for the Lord, an habitation of God by the ſpirit: which J teach thee as my ſelfe haue learned it from that greateſt, and chiefeſt <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chitect Chriſt Ieſus.</hi> by the direction of his holy word. For all that be in Chriſt are likewiſe<note n="c" place="margin">1 Cor. 16, 19.</note> 
               <hi>Temples of the holy Ghoſt</hi> to be built in this world, but to be dedicated in the world to come: (where the glory of the Lord ſhall fill thee with ioy vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable and glorious, as earſt his glory filled the materiall Temple. <hi>Exod: 40.34</hi>) And as the building of theſe ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Temples here is painefull and laborious to fleſh and bloud, ſo the dedication of them there, ſhall bee moſt ioyfull and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.
<pb facs="tcp:21343:5"/> To encourage thee to build, God himſelfe hath laid the chiefe corner ſtone, yea<note n="d" place="margin">1 Pet 5.6.</note> himſelfe is the chiefe corner ſtone, elect and pretious: and all the faithfull are liuing ſtones to bee laid vpon this foundation, and to be built a ſpirituall houſe:<note n="a" place="margin">Aug. Tom in dedicat Templi.</note> 
               <hi>Fide formati, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pe formali, charitate compacti:</hi> ſquared by faith, laid faſt by hope, and cemented together by charitie. Build therefore, or rather be built vpon this firme foundation, both by hearing and practiſing: for if thou build not at all, thou ſhalt be left deſtitute of a<note n="b" place="margin">Eſa 32.2.</note> ſhelter from the wind, and a couer from the tempeſt: and if thou build on any other foundation, thou buildeſt thine owne ruine.<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug.</hi> in Pſal. 101.</note> 
               <hi>Eia ergo (lapides viui) inſtructuram currite, non in ruinam, &amp;c.</hi> Goe to therefore (ye liuing ſtones) come, yea runne to this building, and not to your owne ruine: B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e contented to bee hewen and ſquared by that<note n="d" place="margin">Ier. 23.29.</note> hammer that heweth the ſtones, the lawe of God: and to be poliſhed with the ſtroakes of temptatious, afflictions, and perſecutions here without, for as much as there ſhall not be any noiſe or ſtroake of that hammer heard when he ſhall be perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly poliſhed in the heauenly Sanctuary. Lay the pauement of your building low by contrite humilitie: faſten your ſelues and your faith vpon the maine<note n="e" place="margin">Eph <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 19.</note> foundation ſtones of the Propheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call and Apoſtolicall doctrines: raiſe the walls of your buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding by feruent prayers, and deuout meditations: and adorne your building with good workes, which may bee conſpicuous to the eye of the world (as with turrets and battlements: be pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars to ſupport the weake, and roofes to ſhroud and ſhelter the poore and needy from the tempeſts of their ſeuerall calamities, and neceſsities: ſo ſhall ye be poſſeſſed of the Lord (as temples built for his honour and ſeruice:) by his ſpirit of grace here, and fullneſſe of glory hereafter. That both thou, (Gentle Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, whoſoeuer thou be) and I may thus build, and be built, let vs helpe one another by the mutuall commerce of our feruent, and faithfull prayers.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in the Lord Ieſus, ROBERT BARRELL.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:21343:5"/>
            <head>Faults eſcaped in Printing.</head>
            <p>PAge 2. line 33 for imploy read imply. page 3. line 22. for walles read waters: page 4. line 14, for man read Mammon, page 5 line 30, for certifying reade rectifying, page 6, line 13, read, I wiſh that my words, &amp;c. &amp; page ead. line 28, for conneyed, reade conueyed: page 8 line 22, for <hi>usullarum vnita,</hi> read <hi>multa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum vnitas</hi> &amp; page ead. line 28, for ſtartling, read ſtarting: page 9, line 13, leaue out thereof page 10. line 6. read acknowledge him, &amp;c. page ead. line 28. for Epitom read Epitome &amp; line 29, for ſection, reade perfection. &amp; line 37. between ſee, and ſmell, inſert but: page 12, line 6, for Loe reade Hoe, &amp;c &amp; page ead. line 26, for <hi>Solius</hi> read <hi>ſolus.</hi> page 13, line 2, for mine, reade ruine page 14, line 2, for way, reade wander. page 15, line 2, for phraſes, read praiſes: ibid. line 18, for criri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, aeade criticall. ibid. line 19, for word, read words, page 23, line 27, for till, read while page 30, line 1, for verity, read vnity, &amp; line 23, for vnitie, read vnite. page 31, line 6, for Catholikes, read Cacolikes, &amp; page ead. line 35, for ſupply, read ſupple. page 33, line 26, for <hi>ſectuntur,</hi> read <hi>ſecta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tur,</hi> ibid. line 30, for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> reade <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. page 34, line 38, for <hi>Coſterius,</hi> reade <hi>Coſterus.</hi> &amp; page 36, line 28, ibid. line 26, for ſunne read ſonne. page 40. line 14, for <hi>vt,</hi> read <hi>vel.</hi> page 41. in <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not.</hi> marg. for Anno 3033, read 303, ibid. page 35, for whhle, read whole, page 45, line 21, for <hi>flaida,</hi> read <hi>fluida.</hi> ibid line 35, for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> read <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, page 48. line 9, read <hi>Si reſtitui poteſt,</hi> ibid. line 14, for <hi>Colloguintida,</hi> read <hi>Colloquintida,</hi> ibid. line 27, for mind, conſcience, reade my conſcience Page 50 line vlt, for ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw, reade ouerflow, page 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, line 15, for thee read them, page 61, line 18. for irrecouerable. read irreuocable. ibid line 33, for <hi>Sancte,</hi> read <hi>Sancta,</hi> ibid. line 38, for waſted, read roaſted, page 64, line 5, for right, read righteouſnes, ibid. in marg for <hi>Cypr.</hi> read <hi>Opus,</hi> page 65. line 25, for mine, read ruine, page 67, line 27, for me read one, page 68, line 2, for <hi>malorum,</hi> read <hi>magorum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If thou finde (Gentle Reader) any other faults, either in Orthography or otherwiſe, I pray thee correct them with thy pen: and let not the Printers errors be impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Authour.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:21343:6"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:21343:6"/>
            <head>THE SPIRITVALL ARCHITECTVRE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Text. MATH. Chap. 7. Verſ. 24.25.26.27.</bibl>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>24</bibl> Therefore whoſoeuer heareth theſe ſayings of mine, and doth them, I will liken him to a wiſe man which built his houſe vpon a Rocke.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>25</bibl> And the raine deſcended, and the flouds came, and the winds blew, and beat vpon that Houſe; and it fell not, for it was founded on a Rocke.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>26</bibl> And euery one that heareth theſe ſayings of mine, and doth them not, ſhall be likened vnto a fooliſh man which built his Houſe vpon the Sand.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>27</bibl> And the raine deſcended, and the flouds came, and the winds blew, and beat vpon that houſe, and it fell, and the fall thereof was great.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He bleſſed Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul</hi> termes the <hi>new Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> (which is the Chriſtian Church)<note n="(a)" place="margin">Gal. 4.26.</note> 
               <hi>the Mother of vs all:</hi> and this <hi>mother of all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> (like <hi>Mary</hi> the mother of Chriſt) is<note n="(b)" place="margin">Ser. <hi>119.</hi> de temp.</note> both <hi>a mother and a Virgin.</hi> A <hi>Virgin</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of her moſt pure and <hi>vnſpotted veritie,</hi> which though it be often aſſaulted by curſed haeretiques (the diuells off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring) yet it neuer was, nor ſhall be wholy corrupted:<note n="(c)" place="margin">Mat. 16.18.</note> for the gates of hell cannot preuaile againſt it, being built on the <hi>rocke Chriſt Ieſus. A mother</hi> in reſpect of her <hi>copious faecunditie:</hi> for ſhe is<note n="(d)" place="margin">Cypr. de vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate. Eccl. Sect. <hi>4. &amp; 5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Faecunditatis ſucceſsibus copio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa, a fruitfull mother of children,</hi> bringing forth by her pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of doctrine many ſonnes and daughters to the Lord Almightie; <hi>Illius faetu naſcimur, lacte nutrimur, ſpiritu ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mamur
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:21343:7"/> In her wombe we are bred, by her ſoule or ſpirit we are quickned, by her milke we are nouriſhed:</hi> and her <hi>two breaſts</hi> that yeelds vs this ſweet milk (<note n="(e)" place="margin">Pſal. 19.10.</note> ſweeter to beleeuing ſouls than the hony and the hony combe:) are the two Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>The ſame Church is compared by that holy Father, and bleſſed Martyr S. <hi>Cyprian</hi>
               <note n="(f)" place="margin">Cypr. Epiſt. <hi>73.</hi> Sect. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> vnto <hi>Paradiſe:</hi> the trees wherof are the faithfull: which are<note n="(g)" place="margin">Eſa 61.3.</note> 
               <hi>Germina plantationis Domini, Trees of the Lords owne planting:</hi> and (like the trees plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the riuers of Waters:<note n="(h)" place="margin">Pſa. 1.3.</note>) bring forth their fruites in due ſeaſon; and <hi>the foure riuers</hi> of this Paradiſe (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with theſe trees are watered) are the foure Euangeliſts.</p>
            <p>Theſe riuers (like <hi>Tagus</hi>) haue many <hi>golden ſtreames:</hi> of which this ſermon of Chriſt on the Mount is one of the choiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt: for it may be called <hi>Concio concionum</hi> (as <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> ſweet Epithalamium between Chriſt and his Church is called <hi>Canticum Canticorum</hi>) as being the <hi>key of the whole Bible,</hi> wherein Chriſt opens thoſe treaſures of Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and knowledge which are hid in the old and new Teſtament. Therefore we finde none of Chriſts ſermons ſo largly regiſtred by the Euangeliſts<note n="(i)" place="margin">Ioh. 14.15, 16.</note> as this except his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolatarie ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to his Diſciples before his paſſion: this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his <hi>Primum ſalue, or firſt welcome</hi> to his Apoſtles after their election to the Apoſtleſhip: and that his <hi>vltimum va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le, or laſt Farewel</hi> vnto them immediately before his paſſion.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Praef. Conc.</note>How excellent a ſermon this was it is euident. Firſt, by the Preface or <hi>exordium</hi> thereunto: for it was deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, <hi>In a ſelected place</hi> (<note n="(k)" place="margin">Mat. 5.1.</note> namely, a mountaine,) that the ſublimitie of the place might ſhew the excellencie of the matter:<note place="margin">Ver. 2.</note> 2. <hi>To ſelected auditors</hi> (namely his twelue Apoſtles, and the choiſeſt Diſciples,) and in <hi>an eſpeciall and ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar manner,</hi> intimated: Firſt, <hi>by his preparation thereunto</hi>
               <note n="(l)" place="margin">Luc 6.12.</note>: for he ſpent the whole night before in prayer, which muſt needs imploy ſome conſequence of great importance. Secondly, <hi>By his geſture of ſitting</hi>
               <note n="(m)" place="margin">Aug de Ser. Dom. in Monte.</note>, <hi>Quod pertinet ad dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatem magiſterij,</hi> implying both the dignitie of the ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker (who is<note n="(n)" place="margin">Mat. 23.8.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the great Doctor of his Church) and the weight of the matter. Thirdly, <hi>by the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:21343:7"/> Euangeliſts phraſe of opening his mouth:</hi> which implies not onely our Sauiours earneſtneſſe &amp; intention both of heart and voyce in ſpeaking, but the excellency and diuine per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of his doctrine.</p>
            <p>He who is 1.<note n="f" place="margin">Ier. 24.6.</note> 
               <hi>The eye of God,</hi> by which he looks downe vpon his Church for good and not for euill. 2.<note n="g" place="margin">Eſay 53.1.</note> 
               <hi>The Arme of God,</hi> whereby hee doth both ſuſtaine and imbrace it. 3.<note n="h" place="margin">Eſay 48.13. 1 Pet. 5.8.</note> 
               <hi>The hand of God,</hi> whereby he hath laid the foundation of the earth in the worke of Creation, and pluckt his ſheep out of the mouth of that roaring Lyon the Diuell (as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> did his fathers ſheepe out of the iawes of the Lyon,<note n="i" place="margin">1 Sam. 17.35.</note> &amp; paw of the beare) in the worke of Redemption. 4. <hi>The Face of God,</hi> in whom (as in a Chriſtall glaſſe) we may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold<note n="a" place="margin">Heb. 1.3.</note> the brightneſſe of his fathers glory, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xpreſſe Character of his perſon;<note n="b" place="margin">Ioh. 14.9.</note> 
               <hi>He that hath ſeene me hath ſeene the father.</hi> 5. <hi>The mouth of God,</hi> whereby hee doth both<note n="c" place="margin">Cant. 1.2.</note> kiſſe his Church with the kiſſes of his loue, and inſtruct it with his heauenly Doctrine: heere opens his mouth (as a fountaine of liuing waters) to refreſh the thirſting ſoules of his Diſciples, as earſt hee opened the rocke of ſtone for the refreſhing of the fainting bodies of his <hi>Jſrael,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Pſal. 105.31.</note> ſo that the walles guſhed out, and riuers ran in drye places.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>2</hi> Materia: conc.</note>2 By the ſubſtance or matter of this Sermon; which whoſoeuer ſhall conſiderately read and marke, ſhall finde therein<note n="e" place="margin">Aug. in loc.</note> 
               <hi>perfectum vitae Chriſtianae modum,</hi> a perfect rule or direction for a Chriſtian life, tending to true happineſſe and perfection;<note n="f" place="margin">Mat. 5.48. <hi>Analiſis Conc:</hi> V. 3. <hi>A. v.</hi> 3. <hi>ad</hi> 13.</note> 
               <hi>Be yee perfect, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For therein Chriſt ſhewes vs; firſt, <hi>the Marke</hi> at which wee muſt ayme, namely, true bleſſedneſſe in Gods King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. 2. <hi>The Steps</hi> or <hi>Degrees</hi> whereby wee muſt aſcend vnto it; namely, humility, mourning for ſin, meeknes, &amp;c. for the eight beatitudes are as ſo many ſteps of that<note n="g" place="margin">Gen. 28.12.</note> my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall Ladder of <hi>Jaacob,</hi> whereby we muſt climbe vp vnto Heauen. 3. <hi>The Guides</hi> to conduct vs thither; namely,<note place="margin">A. v. <hi>1.</hi> ad <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> the Miniſters of the Goſpell, who are both the Salt of the earth, to ſeaſon vs with the heauenly Salt of Grace, and the Light of the World, to guide our feete into the way of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:21343:8"/> peace, that we may make ſtraight ſteps to the<note n="h" place="margin">Apoc. 21.2.</note> new Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem and heauenly Sion. 4 <hi>The Norme</hi> or <hi>Squire,</hi> to rule out this way vnto vs, namely the Law of God, <hi>(the rule of Charity and</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Col 3.14.</note> 
               <hi>band of perfection)</hi> which our Sauiour by his diuine expoſition cleeres from Phariſaicall gloſſes and corruptions.<note place="margin">A. v. <hi>17.</hi> ad fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m Cap. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5 The <hi>crooked by-pathes</hi> which wee muſt ſhunne, if wee will keepe vs in the right way to true bleſſedneſſe, and not turne to the right hand or the left; and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: (as t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere is but one right way to a place, but many by-wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es) namely;<note place="margin">Cap. <hi>6.</hi> a. v. ad <hi>19.</hi> A. v. <hi>19.</hi> ad fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, cap. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> 1. <hi>Hypocriſie</hi> in doing our good workes to be ſeene of men. 2. <hi>Worldly Sollicitude,</hi> in lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vp our treaſure in Earth not in Heauen; preferring the ſeruice of man before the ſeruice of God; and caring more for the periſhing vanities of this life, then the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God and his righteouſneſſe.<note place="margin">C <hi>7</hi> a. v. <hi>1.</hi> ad <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> 3. <hi>Vncharitable cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring</hi> of our Brethren, and ouercurious prying into their motes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>V.</hi> 6.</note> whilſt we ſee not our owne beames. 4 <hi>Prophane trampling</hi> vnder our feet (like dogs and Swine) the <hi>preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous pearles</hi> of Gods holy word and Sacraments, and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thoſe that bring them vnto vs with the cruell teeth of malicious obloquy.<note place="margin">A. v. <hi>15.</hi> ad <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> 5. <hi>Liſtning to falſe Prophets</hi> (which are rauening wolues in ſheepes clothing) ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eking vnder the faire pretences of humility, truth, ſimplicity and ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, to prey vpon, &amp; deuoure the ſoules of Chriſts ſheepe. 6. <hi>Omiſſion of holy duties,</hi> namely, of <hi>feruent prayer,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by wee ſhould aske,<note place="margin">A. v. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> ad <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> ſeeke and knocke at the gate of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy: and a <hi>ſerious endeuour</hi> to enter in at the ſtraight gate, and goe on in the narrow way that leads vnto ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:<note place="margin">v. <hi>21.</hi> &amp;c.</note> for as much as a bare verball profeſsion will not ſerue the turne at the laſt day: Not euery one that ſaith vnto mee Lord, Lord, ſhall enter into the Kingdome of Heauen, but he that doth the will of my Father which is in Heauen, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>3</hi> Concluſ. conc.</note>3 By the concluſion, wherein there is an <hi>Emphaticall</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſeeming to limit theſe words of my Text to this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon onely (as containing the ſumme and ſubſtance of the whole Bible) but they may fitly haue a more generall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:21343:8"/> to all the words of Chriſts heauenly doctrine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered to his Church, and recorded in the ſacred Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
            <p>And the Euangeliſt addes;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>V.</hi> 28.29.</note> when Ieſus had ended theſe ſayings, the people were aſtoniſhed at his Doctrine, &amp;c. for hee was the true <hi>Orpheus,</hi> who by the melodious har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y of his heauenly Doctrine drew the rocks, &amp; woods, and wilde beaſts after him; that is, men of rocky and hard hearts (as the Phariſies) and as ſauage in ſinfulneſſe as the wilde beaſtes, namely, Sadduces and Publicans:<note n="a" place="margin">Luk. 6.17. Ioh. 6.2.</note> who flocked from all quarters of Iudea, Samaria, Galile, &amp;c. to heare his diuine doctrine, and behold his Almighty miracles; which they ſaw and heard with aſtoniſhment and admiration, ſaying; neuer man ſpake like this man<note n="b" place="margin">Cap. 7.46.</note>. Theſe words are the concluſion, and application of this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Sermon; for this wiſe maſter builder doth not onely lay the foundation and raiſe the walles, but roofes the top, and perfects the building: this heauenly Husbandman doth not onely plant and ſow by doctrine, but water by Application, that the ſeed may yeeld the more copious increaſe, as he doth elſewhere;<note n="a" place="margin">Ioh. 13.17.</note> 
               <hi>Jf yee know theſe things, bleſſed are yee if yee doe them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein the<note n="b" place="margin">1 Pet. 2.25.</note> 
               <hi>chiefe Shepheard and ſupreame Biſhop of our ſoules</hi> teacheth all his ſubordinate Paſtors, (eſpecially in theſe dayes wherein there is<note n="c" place="margin">Beza.</note> 
               <hi>much ſcience but little con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi>) to bend th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ir endeauours rather<note n="d" place="margin">Bern.</note> 
               <hi>ad imbuenda cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da, quam exprim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nda verba,</hi> to reforme mens liues, then ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to tickle their itching eares or informe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ir curious vnderſtandings: and to ſeeke, not ſo m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch<note n="e" place="margin">Phil 2.21.</note> 
               <hi>the things that are their owne</hi> (that is, their owne vai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> glorious applauſe by curious ſtraines of wit, or painting ouer their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons with the Vermillion of humane Eloquence:) <hi>as the things that are Ieſus Chriſts,</hi> by certefying m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and conuerſations; and ſeeking to bring home many ſheepe to Chriſt his folde, many ſoules to his Kingdome. Otherwiſe thoſe croking Frogs of Rome, (I meane the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites and Seminary Prieſts) which now more then euer ſwarme in our Coaſts, like the Graſhoppers and Cater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pillers
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:21343:9"/> of<note n="f" place="margin">Ex. 10.12.</note> Egipt will ſtill get ground of vs, while we ſeeke to pleaſe mens eares, and they to worke vpon their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences (the ſtrongeſt band to tye men faſt to God and his ſacred truth) and ſo in time the Iſraelitiſh Prouerbe may be inuerted to our great ſhame and the ſcandall of our Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: <hi rend="sup">h</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">1 Sam. 18.7.</note> 
               <hi>Dauid hath but his</hi> 1000. <hi>and Saul his</hi> 10000.</p>
            <p>Pardon therfore my plainneſſe (Right Honourable, &amp;c.) If I ſtriue that my doctrine may be deliuered<note n="h" place="margin">1 Cor. 2.4.</note> rather with <hi>the euidence of the ſpirit and power,</hi> then with the <hi>enticing words of mans wiſedome</hi> and eloquence: for my deſire is not to pleaſe carnally, nor to tickle the eares of the curious; but to win thoſe that are truely religious to a conſtant perſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in truth and godlineſſe: and I wiſh that wordes may be vnto you as <hi>nailes and goads faſtned by the maſters of the Aſſemblies</hi> to pricke you forward to good workes,<note n="i" place="margin">Eccleſ. 12.11.</note> and make you cleaue faſt to Chriſt and his truth continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally.</p>
            <p>Concerning the ſenſe of the Text, I finde a difference a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Interpretors.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Some by this houſe built on a rocke, vnderſtand the Chriſtian Church in Generall, built on the <hi>rock of Chriſtian Doctrine,</hi> which is called,<note n="a" place="margin">1 Tim. 3.15.</note> 
               <hi>The Houſe of the liuing God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of this Houſe 1. <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> is the chiefe <hi>corner ſtone</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Eph. 2.19.20.</note>.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The <hi>Prophets and Apoſtles foundation ſtones,</hi> and</p>
            <p n="3">3 The <hi>faithfull liuing ſtones</hi> made a ſpirituall houſe<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Pet. 2.5.</note>.</p>
            <p n="4">4 The two <hi>oppoſite walles</hi> are the <hi>Iewes and Gentiles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5 The <hi>foure corners</hi> of the Houſe, are the <hi>foure Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6 The <hi>Pillars</hi> are the <hi>Prelates</hi> of the Church.</p>
            <p n="7">7 The <hi>Windowes</hi> wher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>by the light is conneyed vnto it, are the <hi>Paſtors and Doctors</hi> of the Church.</p>
            <p n="8">8 The <hi>Dore</hi> is <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> the dore of the ſheepe<note n="d" place="margin">Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 10.7.</note>.</p>
            <p n="9">9 The <hi>Curtaines</hi> wherewith this Houſe, or holy Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of God is adorned are the <hi>Precepts of the Law, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of the Goſpell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10 The <hi>Table</hi> of this Houſe is the ſacred <hi>Scripture</hi> &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Euchariſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12 The <hi>ſpirituall meat</hi> ſet vpon this Table, is <hi>Chriſt</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Ioh. 6.31.</note> the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:21343:9"/> celeſtiall Manna, the bread of life broken to vs in the Word and Sacraments.</p>
            <p n="13">13 The <hi>Veſſels of honour</hi> appertaining to this Houſe, are<note n="f" place="margin">Rom. 9.22, 23</note> the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eſſels of mercy</hi> prepared vnto glory; and the <hi>Veſſels of diſhonour,</hi> are the <hi>Veſſels of wrath</hi> prepared to deſtruction.</p>
            <p>For the viſible Church is like<note n="h" place="margin">Gen. 7.2. &amp; 8.7.8.</note> 
               <hi>Noahs Arke,</hi> which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained both cleane and vncleane Beaſts; and had in it as well the greedy Rauen, that flying out of it neuer returned againe, as the harmleſſe Done, which out of the Arke found no reſt for the ſoale of her foot, but with an Oliue branch in her mouth returned to the Arke againe.</p>
            <p>This was figured in<note n="i" place="margin">Gen. 4.1.</note> 
               <hi>Adams</hi> family,<note place="margin">Typ Eccl: viſib.</note> which had in it a bloody <hi>Cain</hi> as well as an innocent <hi>Abel;</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">&amp; 9.18: &amp;c.</note> in <hi>Noahs,</hi> which had a curſed <hi>Cham</hi> as well as a bleſſed <hi>Shem</hi> and <hi>Japheth;</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">&amp; 21.9.</note> in <hi>Abrahams,</hi> which had a perſecuting <hi>Jſhmael</hi> as well as a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted <hi>Iſaack:</hi> and in <hi>Iſaacks,</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">&amp; 25.33.</note> which had a prophane <hi>Eſau</hi> ſelling his Birthright for a meſſe of Pottage, as well as a godly <hi>Iacob</hi> that obtained the Bleſſing<note n="n" place="margin">&amp; 27.27.</note>.</p>
            <p>But the wicked,<note place="margin">Jn vnitate Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae non cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris Eccl. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexan: de Hales.</note> although they bee in the vnity of the Church viſible; yet not in the vnity of the Churches body myſticall: or if they be, it is but as corrupt humours are in the body naturall; (which muſt be purged out before the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy can be healthy and ſtrong) but not as ſound, ſollid and ſubſtantiall parts of the ſame body.</p>
            <p>For of thoſe that liue in the viſible Church there are three ſorts: 1 Some are members thereof by Profeſſion on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, 2 Others both by profeſſion and affection for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, but not in reſolution, 3 Others both by profeſsion, affection and reſolution, hauing their hearts faſt knit vnto God for euer. And of Profeſſors there bee foure ſorts. 1 Some profeſſe the Cnriſtian faith but not wholly and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely, as Heretickes: 2 Others profeſſe the whole ſauing truth, but not in vnity; as Sciſmaticks. 3 Others profeſſe the whole truth in vnity, but not in ſincerity, nor with a reſolute and vndaunted conſtancie: as temporizing hyppocrites; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Expoſit. </seg>2</label> and all theſe 3 ſorts build vpon the ſand, 4 Others profeſſe the whole ſauing truth in vnity and ſincerity, and with an ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refragable conſtancie: and theſe only build vpon the rocke.<note n="a" place="margin">Mat 25.2.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:21343:10"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Expoſit. </seg>2</label> 2 Other Interpretors vpon this place vnderſtand not the Church in generall, but the particular members of the Church: whereof ſome are wiſe, ſome fooliſh builders: as elſewhere<note n="a" place="margin">Mat 25.2.</note> they are compared vnto wiſe and fooliſh Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The wiſe Builders are they, that both by hearing and practiſing build their faith on the <hi>rocke Chriſt, and his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred truth;</hi> whoſe faith, neither the <hi>raine of proſperity</hi> can cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eaken, nor the <hi>flouds of aduerſity</hi> vndermine, nor the <hi>winds</hi> of <hi>diabolicall ſuggeſtions</hi> ſhake downe and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw; becauſe the foundation on which they are built is immoueable; namely, <hi>the rocke Chriſt, and his ſacred truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 The fooliſh builders are they that by bare hearing without due practiſing, build their falſe &amp; temporary faith, vpon the ſands of humane traditions, or their owne vaine <hi>fancies and ſuperſtitions,</hi> which euery <hi>win of vaine doctrine, ſtorme of affliction,</hi> or <hi>tempeſt of temptation</hi> may eaſily o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow, becauſe it is built on the ſand, and the fall of ſuch buldings and builders will be great, becauſe they fall finally, totally, irrecouerably from Gods grace and glory, into the bottomleſſe pit of perdition and deſtruction.</p>
            <p>But this difference ſeemes to me rather verball then reall: becauſe the Church is nothing els but a <hi>Mullarum vnita vel potius vnanimitas animarum;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bern: Serm: <hi>61:</hi> in Cant:</note> a collectiue, conſiſting of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny particular men conioyned in the generall Profeſsion of the ſame Chriſtian faith: though ſome bee true Iſraelites, ſome curſed Edomites, ſome profeſsing the truth in ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, others in hypocriſie; ſome conſtantly cleauing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to euen in the mouth of danger, others quickly ſtartling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide from it like a broken bow.</p>
            <p>This Text ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fore is <hi>Gods fanne,</hi> to diſcerne this corne from that chaffe: <hi>His true touchſtone</hi> to trye this pure gold from that counterfeit copper: and the iuſt ballance of his Sanctuary to diſcerne th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> weight of a ſound, ſollid, and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere profeſsion of Chriſtianity, from that which is deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vppon the weights, and lighter then vanity it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Diuiſion: </seg>
               </label> For it doth expreſſe a <hi>threefold difference betweene wiſe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:21343:10"/> and fooliſh builders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, in the <hi>manner of their building:</hi> for the wiſe buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders perfect their building both by hearing and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſing: but the fooliſh builders leaue it vnperfect, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, but not practiſing.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, in the foundation of their building; the wiſe build vpon a ſure and immooueable foundation, namely a Rocke: but the fooliſh, either on none, or a weake foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation; namely, the ſuperficies of the earth or the ſand.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, in the effect and iſſue of their building: for whereas both buildings are violently aſſaulted and beat vpon by raine, ſtormes, and wind: the one ſtands faſt like Mount Sion<note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. 125.1.</note>, &amp;c. the other thereof falls downe flat, and the fall thereof is great.</p>
            <p>Both begin w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll, and conſent in the firſt act, namely, of hearing Chriſts words, (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">V. 24. &amp; 26.</note> &amp;c.) Whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer heareth, &amp;c. but in the latter, they differ as farrre as the Eaſt is from the Weſt, or the heauen from the earth: for the one conioynes hearing and doing: (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) heares and doth them, v. 24. the other diſioynes what God would haue conioyned (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) hearing, but not doing, v. 26. And this is that which makes ſuch a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or wide diſtance between them: Firſt, <hi>in their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties:</hi> the one ſort being tearmed wiſe, the other, fooliſh builders: Secondly, <hi>in their worke:</hi> the one building on the rocke: the other on the ſand: Thirdly, <hi>In the ſucceſſe of both:</hi> for the iſſue of the one building is firme ſtability; but of the other vtter ruine.</p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <p>The firſt difference betweene theſe wiſe and fooliſh buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, is in the manner of their building: the firſt, by hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring onely: the ſecond, by hearing and practiſing. But both heare: for the <hi>eares</hi> are the <hi>open doores</hi> by which the knowledge of thoſe things entereth into the ſoule which haue no viſible ſpecies for the eyes to apprehend:<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 10.17.</note> faith comes by hearing; which is the<note n="b" place="margin">Heb. 11.1.</note> euidence of things not ſeene. Inſomuch as the Centurion (who ſaw Chriſt cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified) beleeued not on him by ſeeing, but by hearing: for hearing him giue vp the ghoſt with a loud cry (contrary to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:21343:11"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:21343:11"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:21343:12"/> the nature of that lingring death:) he concluded<note n="c" place="margin">Mar. 15.36.</note>, <hi>Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this was the Sonne of God</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Ber. Ser: <hi>28.</hi> in Cant.</note>. <hi>Auditus iuuenit quod non viſus: oculum ſpecies fefellit, auri veritas ſe infudit:</hi> His eyes ſaw him<note n="e" place="margin">Eſa. 53 2, 3.</note> 
                  <hi>deſpiſed and reiected of men, a man full of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes, hauing no forme nor beautie that he ſhould be deſired:</hi> but by his <hi>voice</hi> he beleeued, and acknowledged to bee the Sonne of God, not by his <hi>face:</hi> being herein a patterne for all Chriſts ſheepe, and an Idea of them all<note n="f" place="margin">Ioh. 10.27.</note>, <hi>My ſheepe heare my voice, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aquin.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Q.</hi> 12.</note>The Scholemen ſay there is a threefold booke wherein we know God: Firſt, <hi>of nature:</hi> ſecondly, <hi>of Scripture:</hi> thirdly, <hi>of life.</hi> By the two firſt we know him in this life, (but in part and as it were in a gl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe darkely:) but by the third, we ſhall know him <hi>in the life to come, when wee ſhall ſee him face to face.</hi>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">1. Cor. 13.9.</note>
               </p>
               <p>For the learning of the <hi>firſt booke</hi> wee neede vſe nothing but our <hi>eyes</hi>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">Rom. 1.20.</note>, for <hi>the inuiſible things of God (to wit his eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall power and Godhead) are by the creation of the world made viſible.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">Aug <hi>5.55.</hi> in Joh Tom. <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note>Aske the ornament of the heauens: namely, the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the <hi>Sunne</hi> (the beautie of the day, and the <hi>eye of the world:</hi>) and the ſplendour of the Moone, and order of the Starres: (the ſolace and ornament of the night:) aske the aire repleniſhed with <hi>birds (natures quiriſters)</hi> who by their pleaſing notes, and chirping voices dayly chaunt out the prayſes of their Creator: aske the earth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorned with trees, and plants, and repleniſhed with foure-footed beaſts and creeping things, and made the'receptacle &amp; habitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of (Man <hi>the litle world, the epitom of Gods work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip,</hi> and <hi>idea of diuine ſection.</hi>) Laſtly, aske the <hi>ſea, (the profound volume of Gods wonders,</hi> ſwarming with admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and innumerable ſorts of Fiſhes:) aske them all, and they will really anſwer thee: <hi>The Almightie hath created vs:</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Vniuerſus mundusn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l aliud eſt quam deus explicatus. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenag.</note> for the whole world is nothing els but <hi>a large booke wherein God is expreſſed:</hi> whoſe <hi>creatures</hi> are ſuch <hi>faire Characters</hi> that we may reade them running. We need but looke and learne, ſee and perceiue: yea, we may not onely <hi>ſee,</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Cypr. de card. C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. operibus.</note> 
                  <hi>ſmell, taſt,</hi> and <hi>feele</hi> how gratious the Lord is, when
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:21343:12"/> we ſmell, taſte, and feele his creatures.</p>
               <p>For the learning of the ſecond booke, we muſt vſe both our eyes and eares, in reading and hearing: but eſpecially our eares; for although reading of the Scripture be no ſmall edifying: (as appeares by the fruit thereof in the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites<note n="c" place="margin">2. Reg 33.2. &amp;c</note> when the booke of the law was read by <hi>Hilkiah</hi> the Prieſt, in the dayes of <hi>Ioſiah,</hi> and<note n="d" place="margin">Neh. 8.31. &amp;c.</note> by <hi>Ezra</hi> the Scribe, in the time of <hi>Nehemia</hi>): yet <hi>hearing of the Scriptures ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and applyed by preaching</hi> is a more powerfull meanes to aedification and ſaluation: for many<note n="e" place="margin">Act. 8.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> (with the Eunuch) may reade the Scriptures, and not vnderſtand them, vntill the liuely voice of ſome <hi>Philip</hi> be as a key to open the clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet of Gods hidden treaſures, (that is, the myſteries of the Goſpell) vnto them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dignum eſſet per ſuperiores oculorum feneſtras veritatem intrare in animam, &amp;c.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ber. Ser. <hi>38:</hi> in cant.</note> 
                  <hi>It were to be wiſhed that the light of truth might enter into our ſoules by the windowes of our eyes:</hi> but this is reſerued for vs in the life to come, when we ſhall with moſt pure and perfect eyes reade in the booke of life, and ſee God face to face. But now wee receiue the remedy as the diſeaſe firſt crept in vpon vs.<note n="f" place="margin">Gen. 3.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Euah</hi> was ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by hearkning to the voice of the diuell, we muſt bee conuerted by hearkning to the voice of God,<note n="g" place="margin">Nunc vnde irrepſit morbus inde remedium intrat: vt per eandem veſtigia ſequatur vita mortem; tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bras lux: vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num ſerpentis antidotum ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatis. Jbid.</note> that ſo life may enter into our ſoules by the ſame gate, by which death entered, and light come into the houſes of our ſoules by the ſame windowes, by which darkneſſe did: and the antidote of truth (Chriſts owne confection) may be taken of vs in the ſame cuppe wherein we firſt dranke the poyſon of that old ſerpent: namely, by hearing.</p>
               <p>The ſacred Scriptures are the myſticall Paradiſe of God, in the midſt whereof grow the <hi>two trees of knowledge and life:</hi> the fruites whereof are to bee gathered of vs by theſe two hands of reading and hearing: but hearing is the right hand: that is, the more actiue and effectuall. The word of God is the <hi>well of ſaluation,</hi> whence flowe riuers of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of life, that make glad the city of God, (<hi>.i.</hi> his true Church) and our eares are the channels by which the ſtreames of theſe liuing waters doe flow into our ſoules.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:21343:13"/> It is alſo<note n="a" place="margin">1. Pet. 2.2.</note> 
                  <hi>ſincere milke to nouriſh vs,</hi> flowing from the <hi>two breaſts of Chriſt (.i. the two Teſtaments:)</hi> and our hearing is as the mouth whereby we ſucke this ſincere milke that we may grow thereby.</p>
               <p>Wherefore let vs hearken to that great proclamation of the King of Kings<note n="b" place="margin">Eſa. 55.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, &amp;c.</note>: <hi>Loe, euery one that thirſteth come to the waters,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Let vs not ſpend our money</hi> (as too many doe) <hi>for that which is not bread, and our labour for that which ſatisfieth not:</hi> (preferring like ſwine, huskes, and acornes before better food:) but let vs come vnto God, and <hi>encline our eares to him, that our ſoules may liue,</hi> &amp;c.<note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 119.24.</note> 
                  <hi>Let his ſtatutes be our delight, and our counſailors.</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Luc. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.39.42.</note> Let vs chooſe <hi>Maries</hi> better part (namely to ſit at Chriſts feet, and heare his preaching:) ſaying with S. <hi>Peter,</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Ioh. 6.68.</note> 
                  <hi>Maſter, whither ſhould wee goe from thee? thou haſt the words of eternall life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For if we leaue him and his ſacred word to hearken to vnwritten traditions, Popes decretalls, Schoolemens laby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinths, Ieſuites Pamphlets, or Seminary Prieſts buzzing ſuggeſtions, inciting vs to ſet vp the<note n="f" place="margin">1. Sam. 5.3.</note> 
                  <hi>Idol Dagon</hi> with the Arke of God in the temple of our ſoules, or<note n="g" place="margin">2 Reg. 18.21</note> to diuide our hearts betweene <hi>God and Baal</hi> (ioyning with the worſhip of the true God and his Sonne Chriſt, the worſhip of Saints, Angells, Bread, Images, Reliques, &amp;c.) we commit a <hi>double euill,</hi> wee leaue the <hi>fountaine of liuing Waters,</hi> and digge to our ſelues <hi>broken ceſternes that can hold no water,</hi> Ier. 2.13.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">Ber Ser. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>8.</hi> in Cant.</note>
                  <hi>Solius habet auditus verum qui percipit verbum: None heares the truth but hee that hearkens to the word of truth:</hi> for the <hi>word of God</hi> alone is that<note n="i" place="margin">Apoc. 1 16.</note> 
                  <hi>two-edged-ſword,</hi> which commeth out of the mouth of Chriſt: which is<note n="k" place="margin">Heb. 4.12.</note> mightie in operation, and ſharper than any two edged ſword (to cut downe error, and kill ſinne in vs,) entring into the diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding aſunder of the ſoule, and ſpirit, &amp;c.<note n="a" place="margin">Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 6.20.</note> As the ſound of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ammes hornes (Gods power accompanying it) made the walls of <hi>Iericho</hi> to fall: ſo the mightie voice of Gods word (if rightly heard of all, by the vertue of his ſpirit ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companying the ſame) would make the walls, not onely, of <hi>myſticall Babell,</hi> but of hell it ſelfe to reele and totter, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:21343:13"/> fall flat downe, and the whole kingdome of Sathan to come to mine: for it is<note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 1 6.</note> 
                  <hi>the power of God vnto ſaluation:</hi> and it will make the Prince of hell recoyle and giue backe, and fall to the ground<note n="c" place="margin">Ioh. 28.6.</note>, as the powerfull voice of Chriſt made <hi>Iudas</hi> and his confederates goe backeward and fall to the ground.<note n="d" place="margin">Ber. Dom. <hi>7.</hi> poſt Pent.</note>. And this <hi>glaſſe of truth</hi> deceiues no man, flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters no man, but truely and impartially ſhewes euery man what he is, that no man be caſt down with needleſſe feares, nor lifted vp with vaine preſumptions. Alſo it ſupplants vice, and implants vertue in vs: baniſheth our vaine, and cheriſheth our good deſires: layes our ſinnes before our faces, and ſo humbles our proud and loftie lookes, and throwes vs downe before Gods footſtoole, with godly ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and true compunction for them, and then raiſeth vs vp againe with pretious promiſes, and vnſpeakeable comforts in the tender mercies of a compaſsionate father, and ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne merits of a ſoule-ſauing Sauiour.</p>
               <p>Theſe effects hath this powerfull word of Chriſt in all at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiue, deuout, and religious hearers: if it haue not in all, it is becauſe many heare amiſſe: (as<note n="e" place="margin">Iac. 4.3.</note> 
                  <hi>many aske and receiue not becauſe they aske amiſſe:</hi>) for ſome haue<note n="f" place="margin">Mat. 13.9.</note> hearing, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers vnhearing eares: ſome heare the word and keepe it, others heare and ſleight it<note n="g" place="margin">c. 7.6.</note>; treading this <hi>pretious pearle</hi> (like filthy Swine) vnder their feet, in the mire of their ſins; and rending thoſe with the teeth of malice and obloquy that bring it vnto them: therefore Chriſt makes this firſt maine difference or oppoſition betweene the hearers of the word: that the one ſort are<note n="h" place="margin">Rom. 2.13.</note> 
                  <hi>not hearers onely, but doers of the word</hi> (who are the <hi>wiſe builders</hi> and ſhall be iuſtified:) but the other ſort are<note n="i" place="margin">Iac. 1.22.</note> 
                  <hi>not doers of the word, but hearers one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> deceiuing their owne ſoules: who are <hi>fooliſh builders,</hi> and ſhall be condemned, for they with their building ſhall come to ruine.</p>
               <p>There be diuers ſorts of vnprofitable hearers.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Some haue <hi>dull eares,</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 13, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>4.</note> 
                  <hi>hearing they heare, but doe not vnderſtand.</hi> Theſe are no better for their being in the Church than the Churches pillars: for either (<note n="b" place="margin">Act 20 9.</note> with <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichus</hi>) they ſit ſleeping while the miniſter is preaching:
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:21343:14"/> or if their eyes wake, their hearts are a ſleepe: for (like men in a dreame) their hearts waue after their fancies, and are ſo firmely fixt on their worldly profites and carnall plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures that (like <hi>Idols in the Temple</hi>)<note n="c" place="margin">Pſa. 115 5, 6.</note> they haue eyes and ſee not, eares and heare not: and although the ſound of the word beat their eares neuer ſo much, yet the ſound of the world, and the fleſh beates it backe againe.</p>
               <p>Theſe although they can hunt <hi>Mammon</hi> dry-foote in their ſhops all the weeke, and neuer be weary: or ſpend whole dayes and nights in a Tauerne, ſacrificing to <hi>Bac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus:</hi> yet they thinke one houre too much to be ſpent in the Temple, whereby thoſe<note n="d" place="margin">Mat. 8.34.</note> Gadarenes make it apparant that in their account <hi>hara domeſtica</hi> is preferred before <hi>ara do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minica,</hi> their Mammon before Chriſt, the world before the word, and their owne Swineſties before Gods San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Some haue curious eares liſtening (like Athenians) after nouelties: and hearkning after quaint phraſes, and curious ſtrains of wit, more than after wholeſome doctrine: like a child who deſires to drinke out of a painted glaſſe, more to pleaſe his fancie than to quench his thirſt: or an Epicure at a feaſt, who makes choiſe of ſuch meates as are moſt delicious, not moſt wholeſome: as if they accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the word of God no better than<note n="e" place="margin">Ezec 33 31, 32</note> a Fidlers ſong, wherein men regard more the pleaſantneſſe of the voice, and ſweetneſſe of the muſicke, than the ſoundneſſe of the matter.</p>
               <p>Yet when I condemne a curious and ouerdelicate eare, I doe not commend a barbarous ruſticke eare which will not haue wholeſome doctrine adorned with fit and ſignificant phraſes<note n="f" place="margin">Pſa 45.14.</note> which are <hi>the ſpouſes embroydered garment</hi> of nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle worke to cloath and adorne her. The meane betweene both is to bee held: 1. That wee deſire not to heare fine words without matter (which are like a guilded boxe that hath nothing in it:) nor rude and idle battologies (which are like the <hi>Chaos</hi>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">Ouid Metaph, li. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note>, <hi>Rudis indigeſtaque moles,</hi> a confuſed and diſordered heape of words, without either methode or matter: but <hi>ſound doctrine adorned with fit and ſignificant
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:21343:14"/> phraſes,</hi> free from <hi>the enticing words of mans wiſedome,</hi> and yet<note n="a" place="margin">1. Cor. 2.4.</note> in <hi>the euidence of the ſpirit and power:</hi> which is like<note n="b" place="margin">Ioh. 12.3.</note> 
                  <hi>Maryes</hi> Alablaſter Boxe full of precious oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Some haue<note n="c" place="margin">2. Tim. 4.3.</note> 
                  <hi>itching eares,</hi> and they muſt bee clawed firſt either with their owne phraſes: for they muſt be Sain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and marked out for Gods children, and the Sheepe of Chriſt, (as if their names alone were enrolled in the booke of life:) and all the Apoſtles and Martyrs (whoſe names and memories the Church hath euer held reuerend) muſt be vnſainted againe to pleaſe their humours: or els ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with <hi>Inuectiues</hi> againſt others whom they maligne: and to this end they magnifie, cheriſh, and deſire to heare onely ſuch preachers whom (like Parrats) they may teach their <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">Perſius Sat. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> and who may bee as hollow Trunkes to carry through them the bullets of reproaches which they ſhoote at others.</p>
               <p>Theſe haue Eagles eyes to obſerue the defects of others, (eaſily eſpying their<note n="d" place="margin">Mat. 7.3.</note> brethrens moles, but not diſcerning their owne beames (<hi>criricall tongues</hi> to cenſure the beſt word and actions: <hi>hypocriticall lookes</hi> to bleare the eyes of the world: but <hi>Harpies hands,</hi> or clawes, to hooke all that comes neere them; and their <hi>eares (like Mindaes gates)</hi> are wider than the whole body of Religion within them, ſo that it doth eaſily runne out at their eares (as <hi>Diogenes</hi> ſuppoſed) <hi>Minda</hi> would doe at the gates) and expires in hearing onely.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Some haue<note n="e" place="margin">Act. 7.51.</note> 
                  <hi>vncircumciſed eares and hearts:</hi> either <hi>foreſtalled with malice and praeiudice</hi> againſt the Preacher, whom they hate (as<note n="f" place="margin">Reg. 22.8.</note> 
                  <hi>Ahab</hi> did <hi>Michaiah</hi>) becauſe hee doth not prophecye good vnto them but euill: and thoſe wreſt all that is well ſpoken to an ill ſence: (as the ſpider turnes the iuice of the ſweeteſt flowers into poyſon:) or els ſo <hi>blockt, and barred vp with their owne hearts luſts,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious obſtinacy, that although the Lord<note n="g" place="margin">Apoc. 3.21.</note> 
                  <hi>knocke</hi> neuer ſo loud and often at the <hi>doores</hi> of their hearts, they cannot, they will not open to him; <hi>for they haue made their</hi>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">Zach. 7.10.</note> 
                  <hi>faces like a flint ſtone, and their hearts like an adamant ſtone, that
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:21343:15"/> they might not heare the voice of the Lord by the mouths of his Prophets, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the Lord (as a iuſt puniſhment of their former ſins and rebellions) hath giuen them<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 11.8.</note> 
                  <hi>the ſpirit of ſlumber,</hi> eyes that they ſhould not ſee, and eares that they ſhould not heare: ſo that they bee poſſeſſed with ſuch a ſenceleſſe ſtupiditie, ſtupid ſecuritie, and ſtiffe-necked obſtinacy, that like the beares which<note n="b" place="margin">Solinu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> c. <hi>39.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Solinus</hi> writes of (though they be wounded they cannot be wakened: or thoſe fiſhes (which<note n="c" place="margin">Ariſt. li. <hi>4.</hi> de hiſt Aeia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ium c. <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> mentions,) which ſleepe ſo ſoundly, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they haue ſpeares thruſt into their ſides, they ſtirre not a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> all.</p>
               <p>Thus many ſorts are there of <hi>vnprofitable hearers</hi> (com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared by Chriſt to <hi>fooliſh builders</hi>) but there is onely one ſort of good and profitable hearers (compared here to <hi>wiſe builders</hi>) namely thoſe who heare the word of God and keepe it: <hi>firmely in their memories, and faithfully in their conuerſations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No man builds wiſely and firmely in this ſpirituall buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, but he that puts in practiſe what he heares:<note n="d" place="margin">Aug de Serm. dom. in monte.</note> 
                  <hi>Non quiſque firmat quae audit niſi faciendo:</hi> No man can well keepe in memorie what he heares but by practizing: but if he forthwith put in practiſe what he heares, thoſe actions will bee ſo many common places to confirme what hee hath heard in his memory.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. v. 24.</note>Therefore hearing and doing, knowledge and obedience, faith, and charitie, truth and ſanctitie, muſt goe hand in hand together in our Chriſtian profeſsion: for<note n="e" place="margin">Lact. de vero cultu. c. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> vertue without knowledge, is like a body without an head, and knowledge without vertue like an head without a body: both monſtrous and abhominable.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">Ioh. 10.27, 28.</note>
                  <hi>My ſheepe heare my voice</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>and I know them, and they follew mee, and I giue vnto them eternall life, &amp;c.</hi> Behold here the fiue principall <hi>Linkes</hi> of the <hi>golden chaine</hi> of our ſaluation: 1, <hi>Election</hi> (my Sheepe,) 2 <hi>Vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi> (heare my voice:) 3. <hi>Iuſtification,</hi> (and I know them) 4. <hi>Sanctification,</hi> (and they follow me:) 5. <hi>Glorification;</hi> and I giue vnto them eternall life, &amp;c. Therefore hee that
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:21343:15"/> will confirme to his owne conſcience his election, and bee a partaker of Iuſtification, and a poſſeſſor of glorification, muſt haue an effectuall vocation, and a ſinccre ſanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, hearing the voice of Chriſt, and following him.</p>
               <p>To heare aright,<note place="margin">Tu recte viuis ſi curas eſſe quod audis.</note> is to be what a man heares out of the word of God he ſhould be: This is the hearing which God requires:<note n="a" place="margin">Deut. 6.3.</note> 
                  <hi>Heare therefore</hi> (O Iſrael) <hi>and obſerue to doe it,</hi> that it may bee well with thee, &amp;c. And that <hi>Samuel</hi> of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers to the Lord,<note n="b" place="margin">1. Sam. 1.9.</note> 
                  <hi>(Speake Lord for thy ſeruant heareth:)</hi> And that <hi>Dauid</hi> promiſeth,<note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 858.</note> 
                  <hi>I will heare what the Lord will ſay concerning me:</hi> And that deuout S. <hi>Bern.</hi> prayes for,<note n="d" place="margin">Ber: Ser. <hi>28.</hi> in Cant.</note> 
                  <hi>Vtinam &amp; mihi aperiat aurem dominus vt intret ad cor meum ſermo veritatis, &amp;c.</hi> Oh that the Lord would open mine eare, that the word of truth may enter into mine heart, and cleere the eye of my vnderſtanding, and cleanſe my will and affections, &amp;c. For if we thus heare, Faith will cleere that eye of the ſoule which infidelitie hath troubled: and obedience open that hard and flinty heart, which diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and rebellion had ſhut vp and cloſed.</p>
               <p>This doing of Gods word conſiſts in two things:<note place="margin">Eſa. 1.16, 17. Rom. 15.8. Eph. 4.22, 23, 24.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. In ceaſing to do euill; and 2. In learning to do well: In caſting off the workes of darkneſſe, and putting on the armour of light: In putting off the old man, and putting on the new, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="1">1. We muſt mortifie ſinne in our earthly members, &amp;c. (<hi>Col.</hi> 3.5.) and crucifie the fleſh with the affections and luſts: <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.24.<note n="e" place="margin">Ber. Ser. <hi>30.</hi> in Cant.</note> which is a kind of <hi>Spirituall Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</hi> And this muſt bee done: 1. Speedily,<note n="f" place="margin">Luc. 12.40.</note> becauſe we know not what day or houre the Sonne of man will come to call vs to an account<note n="g" place="margin">2. Cor. 5.10.</note> for the deedes done in the body, whether they be good or euill. 2. Totally,<note n="h" place="margin">1. Sam. 15, 9, &amp;c.</note> for in deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe ſpiritual Amalekites we muſt not ſpare one <hi>Agag:</hi> neither may we foſter one<note n="i" place="margin">Iud. 16.4. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Dalila,</hi> or<note n="k" place="margin">Mat. 14.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Herodias</hi> in our boſomes, (<hi>.i.</hi> one darling or beloued ſinne) leaſt that one (though we thinke it but a little one, as<note n="l" place="margin">Gen. 19.20.</note> 
                  <hi>Lot</hi> ſaid of <hi>Zoar</hi>) incenſe Gods iuſt wrath, and worke our deſerued deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: for if any of theſe<note n="m" place="margin">Iud. 2. &amp; 3.</note> Canaanites remaine within our borders, they will be prickes in our eyes, and thornes in
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:21343:16"/> our ſides, wounds in our ſoules, and vlcers in our conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, giuing our ſoules no reſt, but ſtill vexing and mole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting vs.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Finally, that wee returne no more<note n="a" place="margin">2. Pet. 2.21, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>2.</note> with the dogge to his vomit, or the ſow that is waſhed to her wallowing in the mire: for it had been better for vs neuer to haue known the way of righteouſneſſe, than hauing knowne it, to turne from the holy commandement giuen vnto vs. A true poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent hates ſinne once repented of, more mortally than<note n="b" place="margin">2 Sam. 13.15.</note> 
                  <hi>Ammon</hi> did <hi>Thamar</hi> after he had defloured her: or<note n="c" place="margin">Gen. 27 35.</note> 
                  <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſau</hi> did <hi>Jacob</hi> after he had ſupplanted him twice, and decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued him both of his birthright and bleſsing. For ſinne is in this reſpect a true <hi>Iacob,</hi> a ſupplanter indeed. 1. It ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plants vs and depriues vs of our birthright, or intereſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the kingdome of heauen, which we ſhould haue had by Chriſt Ieſus the true heire of heauen: 2. It depriues vs of all Gods bleſsings, temporall, ſpirituall, and eternall: and therefore is to be mortally hated, and vtterly reiected.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We muſt doe good,<note n="d" place="margin">Mat 3.8.</note> 
                  <hi>bringing foorth fruites worthy amendment of life:</hi> and<note n="e" place="margin">Col. 1.10.</note> 
                  <hi>walking worthy of the Lord, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauouring to pleaſe him in all things, beeing fruitfull in all good workes and abounding in the knowledge of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And to the end our workes may bee truely good, and ſuch as God accepteth, wee muſt obſerue theſe condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That our ſelues bee in Chriſt, ingraffed into him as branches into the ſtocke, and incorporated as members with their head by the bond of the ſpirit, and hand of faith<note n="f" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Cor. 5.17.</note> 
                  <hi>If any man be in Chriſt let him be a new creature:</hi> Firſt, he muſt be in Chriſt, and then a new creature. It is the axiome of the Schoole Diuines:<note place="margin">Regula Scholaſt.</note> 
                  <hi>Complacentia operis praeſupponit complacentiam perſonae:</hi> The worke can neuer bee accepted, except the perſon be firſt accepted:<note n="g" place="margin">Gen. 4.4.5.</note> as we ſee in <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel.</hi> Therefore S. <hi>Aug.</hi> ſaith of the vertues of the Heathens, (as the iuſtice of <hi>Ariſtides,</hi> the temperance of <hi>Fabritius,</hi> &amp;c.) that they are but<note n="h" place="margin">Aug in Pſ. <hi>31.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Splendida peccata, .i. Gli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring or glorious ſinnes:</hi> and<note n="i" place="margin">Et Ser. <hi>55.</hi> de ver. dom. in Ioh.</note> 
                  <hi>Curſus celerimus praeter viam, .i. a moſt ſwift courſe, but out of the way:</hi> and ſaith moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:21343:16"/>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">Et in Pſal. 83.</note> That <hi>their chickens were trodden vnder foote by God, becauſe they were not hatched in the neſt of the Church:</hi> mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that their good workes were reiected of God, becauſe themſelues were not members of the Chriſtian Church.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That our good workes proceed<note n="a" place="margin">1. Tim. 1.5.</note> from a pure heart, a good conſcience, and faith vnfained: for the ſpirit of grace is the father, and faith the mother of good workes: the one the root, and the other the iuice of that tree that brings foorth good fruit,<note n="b" place="margin">Ber. Ser. <hi>30.</hi> in Cant.</note> 
                  <hi>Nec palmites abſque vite, nec virtus abſque fide;</hi> True vertue can bee no more without true faith, than the branches without the vine in which they grow and by which they liue, and are nouriſhed.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">1. Reg. 6.34.</note>The two doores of the <hi>Sanctum Sanctorum</hi> had folding leaues claſping in each other: to teach vs that the two doores of faith and charity (by which Chriſt enters into our ſoules, as his holy Temples) muſt neuer be ſeparated, but <hi>Se inuicem tenere, .i.</hi> Fold in one the other, and claſpe hands together.<note n="d" place="margin">Leo magnus.</note> 
                  <hi>Sicut enim in fide eſt operum ratio, ſic in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peribus fidei fortitudo:</hi> As faith is the norme or ſquire to rule out our good workees, ſo good workes are the proppe or pillar to vphold and ſtrengthen our faith. For faith and good workes be fundamentall ſtones in the ſpirituall building of our ſoules, to be an holy Temple in the Lord,<note n="e" place="margin">Eph, 2. vlt.</note> an habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God by the ſpirit: but they both leane vpon, relye vpon, and are borne vp, and ſuſtained by the greateſt and chiefeſt corner-ſtone, Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Maldonate</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mald. in loc.</note> therefore, the Ieſuite, doth falſely taxe vs (in his Commentaries vpon this text) for building on the ſand, becauſe wee teach (with S. <hi>Paul</hi>) That<note n="f" place="margin">Rom. 3.28.</note> 
                  <hi>faith alone doth iuſtifie without the workes of the law:</hi> ſeeing wee teach withall, that charity is the life and ſoule of faith: and that a true iuſtifying faith muſt needs be operatiue, and fruitfull in charity:<note n="g" place="margin">Iac. 2. vlt.</note> for as the body without the ſoule, ſo faith with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out charity is dead.</p>
               <p>We teach indeed (and that according to the Scriptures) that in the act of Iuſtification faith is alone:<note place="margin">Theſis nostra. Fides eſt ſola quoad actum iuſtificandi, non ſolitaria quoad actum exiſtendi.</note> becauſe wee beleeue that not any merit of our owne workes, but the merit of Chriſt his perfect obedience actiue and paſsiue
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:21343:17"/> doth purchaſe at Gods hands the remiſsion of our ſinnes, and makes our peace and reconciliation with him: and <hi>faith</hi> alone is the <hi>eye</hi> whereby wee behold Chriſt, and the <hi>hand</hi> of the ſoule which wee ſtretch out to lay hold on him, and to apply the plaſture of his pretious merits to our wounded ſoules, and to open the rich treaſurie or caskenet of his ſpirituall graces vnto vs: thereforethough we teach, that faith is alone in that act (as moſt proper thereunto) as the eye is alone in the act of ſeeing, the <hi>eare</hi> in the act of hearing, and the hand in the act of receiuing (for theſe members performe thoſe offices and no other:) yet wee ſay that faith is not alone in the act of exiſting, but doth coexiſt in the ſoule of the iuſtified man with other graces, (namely, hope, charity, obedience, patience, &amp;c.) as the eye, eare, and hand are not alone in the body, but doe coex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſt with other members.</p>
               <p n="2">2. And <hi>Bellarmin</hi> doth but fight with his owne ſhadow when<note n="a" place="margin">Bellur. li. <hi>4.</hi> de Iuſtificat. ac. <hi>1.</hi> ad <hi>15.</hi>
                  </note> he labors in 14. ſeuerall chapters to proue againſt the Proteſtants the neceſsitie of good workes vnto ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, which we neuer denyed, eyther directly, or by ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary conſequence, as he doth there falſely accuſe vs.</p>
               <p>For we teach them to be neceſſary vnto ſaluation, <hi>Non neceſsitate cauſalitatis ſed conſequentiae: not as meritorious cauſes of our Iuſtification, but as neceſſary effects, concomitan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Theſis noſtra.</note> 
                  <hi>and conſequents thereof:</hi> (as S. <hi>Aug.</hi> taught long ſince<note n="b" place="margin">Aug. de fide &amp; operibus cap. <hi>14</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Sequuntur Iuſtificatum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on praecedunt iuſtificandum</hi>): for this queene of all graces, (a true iuſtifying faith) is euer ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied, and attended on with other graces, and good workes: as<note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 45.9.</note> 
                  <hi>the ſpouſe with her honourable women.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Alſo we teach them to be neceſſary to ſaluation: 1. <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsitate praecepti:</hi> becauſe God hath commanded vs to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme them:<note place="margin">Opera ſunt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaria ad ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem neceſsitate precepti, &amp; me dii, ſed non me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riti.</note> 
                  <hi>for we are his workemanſhip, created in Chriſt Ieſus, vnto good workes which God hath ordayned that we ſhould walke in them,</hi> Eph. 2.10.2. <hi>Neceſsitate medij:</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are the meane and pathway to ſaluation, but not <hi>Neceſsitate meriti:</hi> as if they were not onely the<note n="d" place="margin">Ber. Ser. <hi>61.</hi> in Cant.</note> way to the kingdome, but the cauſe of our reigning there.</p>
               <p>For we vtterly diſclaime that Popiſh doctrine of the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:21343:17"/> of workes. 1. As derogatory to the grace of God, and 2. to the merits of Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
               <p n="1">1 As derogatory to the grace of God: becauſe as Saint <hi>Ber.</hi> ſaith truely,<note n="e" place="margin">Ber. Ser. <hi>67.</hi> in Cant.</note> 
                  <hi>Non eſt quo gratia intret vbi iam meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum occupauit: Deeſt gratiae quicquid meritis deputatur, .i.</hi> Grace is ſhut out of doores where merit hath got poſeſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: whatſoeuer we adde or aſcribe to merit, wee ſubſtract from grace, according to that of S. <hi>Paul,</hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">Rom, 11.6.</note> If it be of grace it is no more of workes, otherwiſe grace is no more grace: But if it be of workes then it is no more of grace, or els were workes no more workes. Now it is the grace of God alone that workes all good in vs:<note n="a" place="margin">Phil. 2.13.</note> 
                  <hi>He worketh in vs both the will and the deede,</hi> &amp;c. and he findes nothing in vs which of it ſelfe (without the helpe of grace) can concurre with his grace in the doing of good: or which may increaſe or adde vnto, but rather decreaſe and blemiſh the perfection of our well doing:<note n="b" place="margin">Aug. ep. <hi>105.</hi> ad Sixtum.</note> 
                  <hi>Cum non liberat niſi gratia, nil iuſtum inuenit in eo quem liberat: non voluntatem, non operationem, non ſaltem ipſam excuſationem.</hi> (Wheras ſaith S. <hi>Aug.</hi>) the grace of God alone frees vs from the bondage of ſinne, it finds nothing good or righteous in him whom it, doth free, not a good will, or a good worke, yea not ſo much as an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe for ſinne,<note n="c" place="margin">Hom. <hi>93</hi> de temp.</note> 
                  <hi>Non enim in te placet niſi quod habes ex deo: quod autem habes ex te diſplicet Deo.</hi> There is nothing in thee (O man) which doth pleaſe God, but what thou haſt from God: whatſoeuer thou haſt from thy ſelfe doth diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe God.</p>
               <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">Juſtitia duplex promiſsi &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biti. Aug. ep. <hi>105.</hi>
                  </note> And it is the meere grace of God that rewards our well doing: for it is <hi>merces indebita,</hi> (an vndeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rued re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward) or if any way due, it is by the iuſtice of Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, not of our deſert: for God when he rewards our good workes, crownes his owne gifts not our merits. So S. <hi>Cypri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Cypr. epiſt. <hi>77.</hi>
                  </note> When God beholds our fortitude and conſtancy in our conflicts with our ſpirituall or temporall enemies, hee approoues of our willingneſſe, and helpes our weakneſſe in the fight, and crownes vs when we haue ouercome: wherein he doth reward in vs what himſelfe hath done, and honours what himſelfe hath performed.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:21343:18"/>2. We diſclaime the merits of workes, as derogatory to the all-ſufficient merits of Chriſt Ieſus: as if theſe alone were not ſufficient to iuſtifie and ſaue vs, but that they muſt be pieced out with our owne merits: wheras S. <hi>Ber.</hi> ſaith<note n="e" place="margin">Ber. Ser. <hi>61.</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Cant.</note>, That the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt is not <hi>pallium breue, (.i.</hi> a ſhort, or ſcanty cloake that cannot couer two, namely, himſelfe and vs) but <hi>largitur larga, &amp; aeterna iuſtitia: .i.</hi> a moſt ample, large, and aeternall righteouſneſſe couering in him the treaſures of his mercies, and riches of his goodnes, and in vs the multitude of our ſinnes.</p>
               <p>Therfore the Saints of God will aſcribe nothing to their owne merits,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug. in</hi> Pſal. 39</note> but all to Gods onely grace and mercy.<note n="f" place="margin">Ber. <hi>5.</hi> Ser. in Cant.</note> 
                  <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo meritum quod gratiam excludat: horreo quicquid de meo eſt, vt meus ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m, &amp;c</hi> I wil haue no merit (ſaith S. <hi>Ber.</hi>) which may exclude grace: I tremble at any thing that comes from my ſelfe, that I ſhould bee my ſelfe alone, and ſtand vpon mine owne feet: It is the grace of God that doth iuſtifie me freely: my merit is the mercy of the Lord, if he be rich in mercy, I am rich in merit.</p>
               <p>I conclude this point with S. <hi>Auguſt,</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Aug. de prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtinat. ſanct. Tom. <hi>7.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Conticeſcant ergo merita quae periere per Adam, &amp; regnet dei gratia per Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum Chriſtum:</hi> Let merits therefore bee ſilent, and not dare to plead for themſelues before the barre of Gods iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, which are loſt in <hi>Adam:</hi> and let the<note n="b" place="margin">Rom, 5.17.</note> grace of God reigne by Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Cond. </seg>3</label> 3. The third condition in the doing of good workes is, that they be ſuch as God hath commanded in his holy word, which is the perfect rule of righteouſneſſe.<note n="c" place="margin">Mich. 6.8.</note> He hath ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thee (ô man) what is good, &amp; what the Lord requireth of thee, namely, to doe iuſtly, and to loue mercy, and to walke humbly with thy God. As in the building of the Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle. <hi>Moſes</hi> was commanded to doe all things according to the<note n="d" place="margin">Exod. 25. vlt.</note> patt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rne ſhewed him in the Mount: ſo in this our ſpiritual building of our ſoules and bodies to be the<note n="e" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Cor. 6.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the Holy Ghoſt, wee muſt haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n eye to the pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne that God hath ſhewed vs in the holy m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>untaine of his heauenly word or els our building will prooue <hi>Babell,</hi> and turne to our owne confuſion.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:21343:18"/>
               <p>For if the good workes we doe be after the<note n="f" place="margin">Col. 2.8 &amp; 23</note> 
                  <hi>traditions of men, and the rudiments of the world, and not after Chriſt:</hi> (as many Popiſh deuotions are) namely, their pilgrima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, inuocations of Saints and Angells, adorations of Saints, reliques, and Images, and building of Monaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries for lazie Monkes, (which are<note n="g" place="margin">Tit. 1.12.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, euill beaſts, ſlow bellies:) then they are at the beſt but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a wil worſhip, and bodily ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe, and profite nothing: of which God may truely ſay<note n="h" place="margin">Eſa. 1.12.</note> who hath required theſe things at your hand?</p>
               <p>But if they bee ſuch as God hath commanded,<note n="i" place="margin">Lact. Jnſtit. <hi>15</hi>
                  </note> ſuch as haue true Religion for their root; and piety, and charity for the two maine branches whereon they grow, then they be accepted of God, and approoued of men, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.18. And ſuch haue beene the good workes of this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable city: (namely, founding of Hoſpitalls for poore Orphanes, decayed Gentlemen, and Tradeſ-men, maimed Souldiers, &amp;c. that their<note n="k" place="margin">Ihb 21.20.</note> Loynes and ſoules may bleſſe you, and bleſſe God for you:) and erecting of Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Schooles for the training vp of youth in good letters, and ſuch like, in which kind of good workes, I dare bee bold to ſay, that our beautifull <hi>Rachel, (.i. true Religion)</hi> hath beene more fruitfull in one age;<note place="margin">See <hi>Willets</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogue of the Proteſtants good workes, annexed to his <hi>Synopſi. Papiſ.</hi>
                  </note> than their <hi>bleare-eyed Leah (.i. blind Popiſh ſuperſtition)</hi> hath beene in many ages. And I heartily pray that in all ſuch good workes yee may abound yet more and more, and that your charitie may be like the good<note n="a" place="margin">2. Reg. 4.6.</note> 
                  <hi>Shunamites oyle, euer flowing till there bee empty veſſels to receiue it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Condit. </seg>4</label> 4. The fourth condition is that they be done to a good end, and with an vpright intention: not that they may be maſques and vizards to couer the vgly faces of crying op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsion, blood-ſucking extortion, cunning fraud, and gri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping vſury from the eyes of the world: for thoſe that doe good workes to ſuch ends are like their Father the Diuell, transforming themſelues into Angels of light, and ſeeming to be Saints, when they be very diuells, and Sathans hell-hounds: neither can ſuch figge-leaues couer their naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe from the eyes of men, much leſſe from the eyes of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:21343:19"/> God:) Nor that they may be trumpets to proclaime, and blow our fame abroad in the world: (as<note n="b" place="margin">Mat. 6.2.</note> the Phariſes in giuing their almes, cauſed a trumpet to be blowne before them;<note n="c" place="margin">Ber. Ser. <hi>30.</hi> in <hi>Cant.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Quot enim &amp; quales piorum botros operum, aut tulit iactantia, aut faedauit inanis gloria?</hi> for how many clu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the grapes of good workes hath pride and vaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glory corrupted, and pluckt off from the vines that bare them?<note place="margin">Bonorum ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum fines.</note>) but the ends of our good workes muſt be theſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Gods glory:</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Mat. 5.16. c. 6.9.</note> 
                  <hi>Let your light ſo ſhine before men, that they may ſee your workes, and glorifie your father which is in heauen:</hi> for that muſt be the prime end of our actions which Chriſt hath taught vs to make the firſt of our petitions: namely, that Gods name may be glorified. And if we glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie God by the fruites of righteouſneſſe here on earth, hee will glorifie vs with a crowne of righteouſneſſe hereafter in heauen.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The good of his Church, and our Chriſtian brethren, whoſe good we muſt tender as our owne, as fellow ſouldiers of the ſame campe, fellow Citizens of the ſame city of God, fellow-ſeruants of the ſame family, and fellow members of the ſame myſticall body.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The ſaluation of our owne ſoules, which wee muſt prize more then the whole world. <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.26.<note n="a" place="margin">Aug. in Pſal: <hi>120.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Noli fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere niſi propter vitam aeternam, ideo fac, &amp; ſecurus facies.</hi> Haue no ſiniſter intention in the doing of thy good workes, but aime therein at thine owne ſaluation, doe them to that end, and thou ſhalt deale ſecurely. For a true Chriſtian (though he muſt renounce his owne merit in his well doing and ſuffering for Chriſts ſake: yet hee may haue an<note n="b" place="margin">Heb. 11.26.</note> 
                  <hi>eye to the recompence of reward,</hi> (with <hi>Moſes:</hi>)<note n="c" place="margin">2. Tim. 4.8.</note> 
                  <hi>to the crowne of righteouſneſſe,</hi> (with Saint <hi>Paul:</hi>) and<note n="d" place="margin">Heb. 12.2.</note> 
                  <hi>to the glory ſet before him</hi> (with Chriſt himſelfe:) as a ſpurre to pricke him forward to well doing, and a cordiall to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort him in his ſuffering. Yea, hee may ſafely expect it alſo without all pride and praeſumption: yet not as due by his owne deſert, but by Gods faithfull promiſe:<note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. 146.6.</note> 
                  <hi>who keepes his fidelity for euer, and</hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">Rom. 2.6.</note> 
                  <hi>rewards euery man according to his workes.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:21343:19"/>
               <p>The good workes done to thoſe ends, may abſolutely, and in euery reſpect be termed good:<note n="g" place="margin">Bonu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> triplex. <hi>1.</hi> In ſe, &amp; cui fit, ſed non faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enti.</note> for the Schoolemen diſtinguiſh of a threefold good worke. 1. Good in it ſelfe, and to him vnto whom it is done, but not to the doer: (as when a man giues an almes to a needy perſon, not out of charity, but out of pride and vaine glory to bee ſeene of men.) 2.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>2.</hi> Jn ſe, &amp; fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cienti, ſed non cui fii.</note> In it ſelfe, and to the doer, but not vnto him to whom it is done: as when out of our charity we beſtow an almes vpon an idle perſon: 3.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>3</hi> In ſe, &amp; cui fii, &amp; facienti.</note> In it ſelfe, and to the doer, and to him alſo to whom it is done: as when wee giue an almes to one that truely wants, not for our own but Chriſt his ſake:<note n="h" place="margin">2. Sam. 9.7.</note> 
                  <hi>As Dauid did good to poore Mephiboſeth for Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nathans ſake.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Applic. </seg>
                  </label> Let me exhort you therefore who (with charitable <hi>Dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cas</hi>)<note n="i" place="margin">Act. 9.36.</note> are full of good workes and almes which ye doe, not<note n="k" place="margin">Mat. 6.1, 2.</note> Phariſaically to cauſe a trumpet to bee blowne before you when ye giue your almes, or to doe your good work<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to be ſeene of men: for then although yee haue the reward ye now looke for, and hunt after vpon earth, ye ſhall looſe the reward which ye ſhould looke for in heauen,<note place="margin">Verſ. 3.</note> your tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall vaineglory will rob you of eternall true glory: but doe them in ſecret, and for the ends before ſpecified, and <hi>your Father which ſeeth you in ſecret will reward you o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Verſ 4.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And the leſſe ye ſeeke for your owne glory on earth, the more ye ſhall obtaine it: the faſter ye flye from it, the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter it will purſue you (as the ſhadow the body:) for a good name is the inſeparable companion of well doing.</p>
               <p>And by doing <hi>bona, bene,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Fructus bone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum operum. <hi>1.</hi> Am<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r.</note> (<hi>i.</hi> Good workes to good ends) ye ſhall vndoubtedly reape theſe fruites: 1. Loue, honour, and reuerence among men: ſo that they will reioyce to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy, and grieue to looſe you, (<note n="a" place="margin">2 Reg. 2.12.</note> as <hi>Eliſha</hi> did for <hi>Elias</hi> at his aſſumption, <hi>My father, my father, the chariot of Jſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell, and horſemen thereof,</hi> and<note n="b" place="margin">Act. 9 39.</note> the poore Widowes who ſtood weeping for the death of charitable <hi>Dorcas.</hi>) 2.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>2.</hi> Conſcien. pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Peace, ioy, and ſolace in your owne ſoules: which is the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all feaſt that God himſelfe makes for them that feede the hungry, &amp;c. 3.<note place="margin">3. <hi>Hon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r.</hi>
                  </note> A good name: which while yee liue ſhall
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:21343:20"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:21343:20"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:21343:21"/> be<note n="c" place="margin">Pro. 3.8.</note> 
                  <hi>health to your nauells, and marrow to your bones:</hi> and when ye dye it ſhall be <hi>a pretious oyntment</hi> to embaulme your bodies in the graue,<note n="d" place="margin">&amp; 15.1.</note> 
                  <hi>as</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Ioh. 12.3.7.</note> 
                  <hi>Maries ſpikenard</hi> embaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Chriſts body at his funerall. 4.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>4</hi> Gloria aeterna.</note> 
                  <hi>An</hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">1 Pet. 1.4. &amp;c. 5. v 4.</note> 
                  <hi>inheritance im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall, and vndefiled, reſerued in heauen for you, and an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marciſcible crowne of glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">Gal. 6 9.</note>
                  <hi>Be not weary therefore of well doing, for if yee faint not, ye ſhall reape without wearineſſe:</hi> namely, loue, honour, ioy, peace, and glory both in earth and heauen.<note n="h" place="margin">Chryſ. in loc.</note> 
                  <hi>Qui deficit in ſemine non gaudebit in meſſe, ſed ſi homo non imponat finem operi, deus non imponet finem remunerationi.</hi> Hee that faints in ſeed time ſhall faile in harueſt: but if a man put no pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod to his perſeuerance in well doing, God will put no end to the reward of his well doing.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>The <hi>2.</hi> gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall part.</head>
               <p>The ſecond difference betweene theſe wiſe and fooliſh builders is in the choiſe of their foundation: the firſt buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding on a rocke, the other on the ſand.</p>
               <p>The principall care of a wiſe builder is to make choiſe of a firme foundation to build vpon: for if the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be immooueable, the whole building will ſtand faſt and firme: but if the foundation faile, all the building (though neuer ſo laboriouſly framed, and artificially compoſed, will fall to the ground, and come to ruine. Now, no founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is ſo firme and immooueable as a <hi>Rocke,</hi> and therefore no building ſo ſtrong as that which is rayſed on a rocky foundation: which will not faile how great a weight ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be laid vpon it, nor be mooued, much leſſe be remooued with any guſts of wind, force of ſtormes, or violence of torrents whatſoeuer.</p>
               <p>A true Chriſtian therefore that heares Gods word, and doth it, is fitly compared to ſuch a wiſe builder that builds his houſe vpon a rocke:<note place="margin">Verſe 24.</note> 
                  <hi>I will liken him, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Expoſ. </seg>
                  </label> 1. By this rocke,<note n="a" place="margin">Aug. Hier. Baſil, &amp;c. in loc.</note> ſome interpreters vnderſtand Chriſt himſelfe: becauſe by the power of his might, the righteous that cleaue vnto him by faith and obedience, are protected and ſtrengthened againſt the violence of all temptations, afflictions, and perſecutions: In which ſence <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith,<note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. 18.2.</note> 
                  <hi>The Lord is my rocke and my fortreſſe, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:21343:21"/>2. Others, by this rocke vnderſtand the inuiolable and immooueable diuine truth of his Sacred word: So <hi>Chryſ.</hi> vpon this text,<note n="c" place="margin">Chryſ. in loc.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: He calls the firme ſecuritie of his owne doctrine a Rocke: becauſe vpon a rocke a man may build ſecurely: and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by hee mooues all his Diſciples to imbrace his diuine do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine:<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Jbid.</note> ſhewing the firme ſoliditie and immutability ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, by the ſolidity and immobility of a rocke: which who ſo builds his faith vpon, ſhall ſtand faſt<note n="d" place="margin">Pſa. 125.1.</note> like Mount Sion that cannot be remooued, but ſtandeth faſt for euer.</p>
               <p>But I thinke both theſe expoſitions may bee conioyned, and by this rocke we may vnderſtand both Chriſt, and his Sacred truth: for<note n="e" place="margin">Ioh. 14.16. c 17.17.</note> as hee is the truth, ſo his word is truth: as he is the life, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t aeternall, ſo his words are<note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>c.</hi> 6.68.</note> the words of aeternall life. And the whole word of truth is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing els but the reuelation and manifeſtation of that ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall word, that increated truth Chriſt Ieſus. For hee is the pith and kernell of the whole Bible,<note n="g" place="margin">Apoc. 1.8.</note> the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the law, and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the Goſpell:<note n="h" place="margin">Aug. Q. in Ex. <hi>73.</hi> &amp; <hi>15.</hi> de ciu. dei c. <hi>18.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Velatus in veteri Teſtamento, reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latus in nouo, in illo praedictus, in iſto praedicatus:</hi> veiled and claſped vp in the old Teſtament vnder obſcure Propheſies, promiſes, types: and figures, and opened or reueiled in the new: for<note n="i" place="margin">Exod 73.9.</note> as the two Cherubins had their faces each to other, and both to the Propitiatory, or mercy-ſeat, ſo the two Teſtaments haue relation each to other, and are mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally confirmed one by the other, and haue both an eye to one and the ſame Chriſt,<note n="k" place="margin">1 Ioh. 2.2,</note> 
                  <hi>who is the Propitiation for our ſinnes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As Chriſt onely is that foundation whereon the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all building of the Church is rayſed in ſome reſpects:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1</hi> Chriſtus Petra</note> name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly firſt, becauſe hee alone is the beginning and fountaine, whence all ſpirituall good originally flowes:<note n="a" place="margin">Iac. 1 17.</note> 
                  <hi>Euery good and perfect gift is from aboue, and commeth downe from the Father of lights, &amp;c.</hi> and the foundation whereon our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, hope, and expectation of any good which wee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect from God groundeth it ſelfe:<note n="b" place="margin">2 Cor 1.20.</note> 
                  <hi>for in him all the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of God are yea and Amen, to the glory of God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:21343:22"/>
               <p>Secondly, becauſe all our perſuaſion of the moſt Sacred and irrefragable authority of diuine truth ſtayeth it ſelfe on him alone, as being the onely<note n="c" place="margin">Mal. 2.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Angell of that great co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant of life and peace,</hi> which God hath made with his Church in him, &amp; reuealed it to his Church by him: (<note n="d" place="margin">Eph. 2.14.16, 17.</note> who is our <hi>peace-maker, and peace-preacher, and our peace:</hi> and the onely inditer of the Sacred Scripture,<note n="e" place="margin">Luc. 1.70.</note> who ſpake by the mouths of all his holy Prophets, which were but<note n="f" place="margin">P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>al. 45.1.</note> the <hi>pens of this ready Writer:</hi>) in which reſpects the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaith truely,<note n="g" place="margin">1 Cor. 3.11.</note> 
                  <hi>Other foundation can no man lay than that which is laid, namely Chriſt Jeſus:</hi> and on this rocke or foundation the Apoſtles themſelues, and their doctrine were founded, or els<note n="h" place="margin">Act 5.37.</note> (as <hi>Gamaliel</hi> ſaith) both they and it would quickly haue come to nought, and fallen to ruine.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>2.</hi> Doctr. Apoſt.</note>So in ſome other reſpects<note n="i" place="margin">Eph. 2.19, 20.</note> the doctrine of the Prophets and Apoſtles is called the Churches foundation, Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus being the chiefe corner ſtone.</p>
               <p>Firſt, becauſe they were the firſt that by their doctrine laid the Churches foundation, and conuerted Infidells to the Chriſtian faith.</p>
               <p>Secondly, becauſe their doctrine (receiued immediately from God by moſt vndoubted reuelation, without mixture of errour, and now left recorded vnto vs in the Sacred Scripture) is <hi>the infallible rule of faith</hi> to all ſucceeding ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations, and that moſt ſure, immooueable, and rocky foundation, vpon which the faith of all Chriſtians may, and doth moſt ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>curely ſtay it ſelfe. Therefore Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith,<note n="k" place="margin">Apoc. 21.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>4.</note> 
                  <hi>The wall of the city of God hath twelue foundation ſtones, and in them were written the names of the Lambes twelue Apoſtles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And herein <hi>Peter</hi> had no preheminence aboue the reſt, except a primacy of order onely: for<note n="a" place="margin">Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er omnes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>quo Eccleſ for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudo ſolidatu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. in Jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. li. <hi>1</hi>
                  </note> Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> ſaith, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Church is aequally founded on the doctrine of all the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles:</hi> for theſe words,<note n="b" place="margin">Mat. 16.18.</note> 
                  <hi>Tu es Petrus &amp; ſuper hanc Petram aedificabo Eccleſiam:</hi> were not ſpoken perſonally to <hi>Peter,</hi> but generally to all the Apoſtles, (who as well as <hi>Peter</hi> did beleeue and confeſſe the ſame faith,) though in token
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:21343:22"/> of vnity they were vttered to one which in vnity did ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaine to all the Apoſtles,<note n="c" place="margin">Vnus pro mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis vnitas, pro <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>niuerſis. Aug. in Pſal. <hi>88.</hi>
                  </note> in whoſe names <hi>Peter</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone made this confeſsion. Moreouer, not <hi>Peters</hi> perſon, or place, but the <hi>faith</hi> which he confeſſed, is that rocke on which the Church is built: as both the whole ſtreame of the Fathers, and the generall counſell of Chalcedon doe te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ide Aug. de ver. dom. Ser.</hi> 13. <hi>Hil. de Trin li.</hi> 6. <hi>Chryſoſt. inc.</hi> 16 <hi>Mat. Theod. in Cant. Pag</hi> 235. <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſ. in cap.</hi> 2. <hi>ad Eph. Epiſt. in Appendice, Conc. Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced.</hi> 13.</p>
               <p>Seeing therefore he was called<note n="d" place="margin">Aug Retract. li. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>21.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Petrus a petra,</hi> from that rocke of faith which he confeſſed, <hi>Thou art the Chriſt the Sonne of the liuing God:</hi> which faith the reſt of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles held, taught, and confeſſed as well as he, and ſealed it with their blood, wee may truely inferre (with S. <hi>Jerome</hi>)<note n="e" place="margin">Hieron. in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos, li. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> that in this reſpect they were rocks (as well as he) where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Church is founded.</p>
               <p>Yea<note n="f" place="margin">Petrus geſsit perſonam Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicut Iudas ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micorum Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti. Aug. in Pſal <hi>108.</hi>
                  </note> S. <hi>Aug.</hi> ſaith farther, that <hi>Peter</hi> in confeſsing Chriſt: and receiuing the power of the keyes ſuſtained the perſon, not onely of the Apoſtles, but of the whole Church Militant, as <hi>Iudas</hi> did of the Church malignant:<note n="g" place="margin">Jdem. <hi>50.</hi> in Ioh c. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Vnus ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus corpus malorum ſignificat quomodo Petrus corpus bono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, corpus eccleſiae:</hi> As one <hi>Iudas</hi> ſignified the whole ſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etie of the wicked, ſo one <hi>Peter,</hi> the whole company of good men, the body of the Church. Therefore from thoſe words of Chriſt to <hi>Peter,</hi> (Thou art <hi>Peter, &amp;c.</hi>) (who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented not the Apoſtles onely, but the whole Chriſtian Church confeſsing the ſame faith:) it cannot bee inferred, that S. <hi>Peter</hi> and his ſucceſſors are that rocke on which the Church is founded.</p>
               <p>Thoſe therefore that build their faith on that foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Prophets and Apoſtles, whereof Chriſt is the chiefe corner-ſtone, by beleeuing, confeſsing, and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing, are thoſe wiſe builders here ſpecified which build their houſes on a rocke.</p>
               <p>For the entire and ſincere beleefe, profeſsion,<note place="margin">Nota Eccleſ. infa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>biler<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of thoſe ſupernaturall verities which God hath reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in his Sonne Chriſt by the miniſtery of the Prophets
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:21343:23"/> and Apoſtles, (and that in veritie) is an infallible note of the true Church, and of a true member of the true Church.</p>
               <p>All other notes without this are falſe, and counterfeite, and may deceiue vs.<note place="margin">Notae fall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>biles.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Antiquitas.</hi>
                  </note>1. Antiquitie without truth is nothing els but<note n="a" place="margin">Cypr. epiſt <hi>74.</hi> &amp; <hi>63</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Vetuſtas erroris:</hi> for we muſt not ſo much attend vnto, or conſider what others haue done or thought fit to be done before vs, as what Chriſt hath done who is before all: we muſt not follow the cuſtome of man, but the truth of God: for the true antiquity is truth it ſelfe deriued from Chriſt<note n="b" place="margin">Eſa. 9.6.</note> the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of aeternitie.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <note place="margin">2. <hi>Succeſsio.</hi>
                  </note>2. Perſonall ſucceſsion without doctrinall is but as<note n="c" place="margin">Mat. 26.1. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iaphas</hi> ſucceeded <hi>Aaron,</hi> and yet was an enemy to the true High Prieſt Chriſt Ieſus.<note n="d" place="margin">Naz in lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem Athanaſis.</note> Such falſe Paſtors, or bad members of the viſible Church ſucceeded the true, and good, as darkneſſe ſucceedes the light, or ſickneſſe, health, or a tempeſt, faire weather, or madneſſe the right vſe of reaſon.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <note place="margin">3. <hi>Vnitas.</hi>
                  </note>3. Vnity without truth is but a diueliſh faction, and like that of thieues and rebells) an accu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſed confederacie, and wicked conſpiracie againſt the God of truth,<note n="e" place="margin">Apoc. 19 16.</note> 
                  <hi>Who is the King of Kings, and Lord of Lords:</hi> Such though they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bine and v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap> themſelues neuer ſo ſtrongly, are but like<note n="f" place="margin">Gen. 49.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Simeon and Leui, brethren in euill;</hi> or like<note n="g" place="margin">Luc. 23 12.</note> 
                  <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late,</hi> that vnited themſelues in a league of friendſhip to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">4. <hi>Vniuerſalitas</hi>
                  </note>Vniuerſalitie or multitude without truth is nothing: for one<note n="h" place="margin">1 Reg. 18.19.</note> 
                  <hi>Elias</hi> teaching and profeſsing Gods truth, and true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly worſhiping the true God of Iſrael, is to be preferred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e foure hundred Proph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ts of <hi>Baal,</hi> though brought vp in <hi>Ahabs</hi> Court, and eating bread at <hi>Iezabells</hi> table: and one<note n="i" place="margin">Luc. 23 42.</note> poenitent thiefe confeſsi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g Chriſt before the high Prieſts and Elders, Scribes, Phariſes, Sadduces, and thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of Iewes perſecuting him.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">5. <hi>Nom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n Catho.</hi>
                  </note>Nor the ſpecious titles of holy, Catholike, Apoſtolike, &amp;c for that Church which hath theſe titles without truth, is like a boxe in an Apothecaries ſhop, which without hath the title of a ſoueraigne antidote written in faire Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:21343:23"/> and within is full of deadly poyſon.</p>
               <p>Bare titles will not ſerue the turne: for thoſe haeretikes in Saint <hi>Bernards</hi> time, who in truth were <hi>Apoſtatici</hi> (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they reuolted from the Catholike faith) tearmed themſelues <hi>Apoſtolici</hi> (though they could ſhew no ſigne of their Apoſtleſhip:<note n="a" place="margin">Ber. Ser. <hi>64.</hi> in Cant.</note>) and in our dayes Popiſh Catholikes tearme themſelues Catholikes, and Iebuſites, Ieſuites, and the Synagogue of luſt, the family of loue.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Applicat. </seg>
                  </label> Be not therefore carryed away from the rocke of Chriſts Sacred truth with any, or all thoſe gliſtering ſhewes which that painted whore of Babylon makes of antiquitie, ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, vnitievniue, rſalitie, or the goodly titles of holy, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike, Apoſtolike, &amp;c. for all theſe are but the<note n="b" place="margin">2 Reg. 9.30.</note> painted face of that whoriſh Iezabell, or her<note n="c" place="margin">Apoc. 17.4.</note> golden cup gliſtering without, but within full of the wine of her abhominations, and filthineſſe of her fornications: the truth of Gods word alone, is that firme and immnoueable rocke on which euery wiſe Chriſtian muſt build the ſpirituall aedifice of his ſoule and conſcience.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>1</hi> Petra regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat.</note>1. This is that rocke out of which wee are ſpiritually hewen: (<hi>Eſa.</hi> 51.2) that is, the <hi>Rocke of our regeneration:</hi> for<note n="d" place="margin">1 Pet. 1.23.</note> 
                  <hi>we are borne againe not of corruptible ſeed, but incorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible, by the word of God which liueth and abideth for euer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Nutrit.</hi>
                  </note>2. The rocke of our ſpirituall nouriſhment vnto ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: whence doe flowe 1. the waters of life to refreſh our fainting ſoules, as<note n="e" place="margin">Exod. 17 16.</note> ſtreames of Waters flowed from the rocke in Rephidim to refreſh the thirſting bodies of the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites. 2. The hony of ſpirituall conſolation, which doth comfort the ſoules of Gods Saints in their ſpirituall Warfarre, more than the hony that<note n="f" place="margin">1 Sam. 14.27.</note> 
                  <hi>Ionathan</hi> taſted com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted his fainting Spirits in his warfare againſt the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtims: for Gods word is ſweeter to the ſoules of his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren than the<note n="g" place="margin">Pſal. 19.10.</note> 
                  <hi>hony and hony combe.</hi> 3. The oyle of deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: for this rocke poures vs out<note n="h" place="margin">Ioh. 29.6.</note> riuers of oyle, to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply our hard hearts, and ſtiffe knees, that our ſoules and bodies may be flexible to the will of God.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <note place="margin">3. <hi>Protectionis.</hi>
                  </note>3. The rocke that ſhelters vs from the tempeſts of temptation, and floudes of affliction and perſecution:
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:21343:24"/>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">Pſal. 104.18.</note> 
                  <hi>as the ſtonie rockes are a refuge for the conies:</hi> for whither ſhould we flye in all theſe for ſhelter but to Chriſt and his word? The Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> ſaith of Chriſt:<note n="k" place="margin">Eſa 32.11</note> 
                  <hi>This man ſhall be an hiding place from the wind, and a couer from the tempeſt, as riuers of Water in a dry place, or as the ſhadow of a great rocke in a weary land.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And <hi>Dauid</hi> of his word,<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal 56.10.</note> 
                  <hi>In thy word will I reioyce, in thy word will I comfort me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">
                  <note place="margin">4. <hi>Salutis.</hi>
                  </note>4. The rocke wherein wee may repoſe vs for reſt and ſafety, (as the<note n="b" place="margin">Cant. 2 14.</note> Doues in the clefts of the rocke:) or as <hi>Moyſes</hi> did<note n="c" place="margin">Exod. 33.22. v. 23.</note> who was put by God into the cleft of the rocke in <hi>Horeb,</hi> and couered with his hand while his glory paſſed by: and in this rocke we may hehold (with <hi>Moſes</hi>) not onely <hi>poſteriora dei,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">5. <hi>Contemplat.</hi>
                  </note> the backe-parts of God, (that is, his wondrous workes, and the acts of his power and iuſtice:) but <hi>anteriora dei,</hi> the foreparts of God, (that is, the face of his mercy, and<note n="d" place="margin">Pſal. 4.6.</note> light of his countenance:) and that in him which is the<note n="e" place="margin">Heb. 1.3.</note> expreſſe character of his fathers ſubſtance, or image of his perſon, namely, Chriſt Ieſus. And with<note n="f" place="margin">1 Reg. 19.11, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lias</hi> ſtanding in the caue of the rocke in <hi>Horeb:</hi>) wee may behold God himſelfe paſsing by vs, not onely in a ſtrong wind, violent earthquake, and conſuming fire of iuſtice by the threatnings of the law, but in a ſoft ſtill voice of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy by the promiſes of the Goſpell.</p>
               <p>Seeing therefore Chriſt and his holy word is the onely rocke.</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>of our regeneration:</hi> without which we lye<note n="g" place="margin">Eph. 2.1.</note> dead in ſinnes and treſpaſſes.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>of our ſpirituall nouriſhment</hi> and conſolation: without which wee can neuer grow to a<note n="h" place="margin">c. 42 3.</note> perfect man in Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>of our ſupportation:</hi> without which wee fall to ruine.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, <hi>of our ſhelter and protection,</hi> without which wee lye open to the ſtormes of all miſeries, temptations, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, and perſecutions.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, <hi>of our diuine contemplation:</hi> wherein we may ſee God and his Sacred myſteries by the eye of faith<note n="i" place="margin">Cor 2.14.</note> which
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:21343:24"/> can nor bee diſcerned by the eye of reaſon: and without which we are<note n="k" place="margin">Apoc. 3.17.</note> miſerable, and wretched, poore, and blind, and naked: let vs build our faith and obedience on this bleſſed rocke, which is immooueable, and cannot be ſhaken, and then we ſhall haue a<note n="l" place="margin">Heb. 12.28.</note> kingdome that cannot be ſhaken, that is, of aeternall glory in heauen.</p>
               <p>All that build not on this rocke are fooliſh builders, and build vpon the ſand, or ſuperficies of the earth without a foundation.</p>
               <p>By the ſand is here meant,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>2</hi> Super arenam aedificare.</note> 
                  <note n="m" place="margin">Faber. Stap. in Loc. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Aliud a petra fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum;</hi> that is, any other foundation of our ſpirituall buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding beſides Chriſt and his Sacred word: namely, mens traditions, or our owne opinions, or falſe miracles, or ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing legends, or the worlds baites, or the diuells ſuggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, &amp;c. all which are fitly compared vnto ſand: 1.<note place="margin">Rat. Simil.</note> for their worthleſneſſe: for ſand is of ſmall or no value: 2. their fruitleſneſſe; for ſand is barraine:) 3. their diſcohae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent incongruity, for yee cannot make a rope of ſand, the parts whereof will not hang together: 4. their inconſtant inſtabilitie, floating like a quicke ſand.</p>
               <p>Euery Haeretike therefore (as<note n="a" place="margin">Hilar. in Loc</note> 
                  <hi>Hilary</hi> ſaith) builds vpon the ſand: becauſe Haereticall doctrines had no firmer ground than mens fancies, and haue no cohaerence either with the truth, or among themſelues. Therefore<note n="b" place="margin">Iren. li. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>13.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Ireneus</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares haeretikes to men labouring of a frenzie: <hi>Quia vm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bras pro rebus ſectuntur:</hi> They purſue their owne ſhad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, and feede themſelues with their owne fancies. And<note n="c" place="margin">Beda in Loc.</note> 
                  <hi>Beda</hi> ſaith, That euery ſinner builds on the ſand, becauſe ſinne hath no foundation to ſtay it ſelfe vpon, nor any reall entity or ſubſiſtence in it ſelfe: for it is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a meere irregularitie, or deflexion from the lawe of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Applicat. </seg>
                  </label> Now there be amongſt vs foure ſorts of men that build vpon the ſand:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1</hi> Papiſts.</note> Firſt, Superſtitious Papiſts: ſecondly, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane <hi>Belials:</hi> thirdly, Greedy Mammoniſts: fourthly, Masqued Hypocrites.</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>Superſtitious Papiſts</hi> (though they would bee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted the onely true Church, and that none built vpon the rocke of truth but they:) build their faith vpon ſandy
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:21343:25"/> foundations. I will not meddle with thoſe ſandy foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons whereon they build the hope of their ſaluation: name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, their owne merits and ſatisfactions, the merits and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſsions of Saints and Angells, and the Popes indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, whereby he exhauſteth the Churches treaſurie (as they tearme it) to fill his owne coffers: but will only ſpeake of thoſe whereon (as maine foundations) they build their faith, forſaking the ſole immooueable rocke on which they ſhould build it, namely, Chriſt and his Sacred truth recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the Scriptures.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Papiſt. Fidei fundamenta tria.</note>And theſe are three: 1. the Churches traditions: 2. the Churches authority: 3. the Popes infallibility: yet theſe three meete in one center, and are deuolued by them into one and the ſame ground or principle of their faith: for they make the Popes mouth the Delphos, that deliuers to the preſent Church the Oracles of the auncient Churches traditions.</p>
               <p>And their Canon Law ſet foorth vnder <hi>Gregorie</hi> the 13. ſaith,<note n="a" place="margin">D <hi>40.</hi> Si Papa.</note> That men doe with ſuch reuerence reſpect the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicall ſea of Rome, that they rather deſire to know the inſtitutions of Chriſtian Religion from the Popes mouth, than from the holy Scriptures.</p>
               <p>But let vs conſider theſe ſandie foundations of their faith ſeuerally.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tradit</hi>
                  </note>1. For <hi>Traditions,</hi> their councell of Trent made a car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall decree<note n="b" place="margin">Hiſt. Conc. Trid:</note> (at the time of a Carnouall) that<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Seſſ.</hi> 4 <hi>Decr</hi> 1.</note> they ſhould be receiued with the ſame reuerence and affection wherwith we receiue the Sacred Scriptures: yea<note n="d" place="margin">Coſteri L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid. c. <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Coſterius</hi> a Ieſuite goes farther, and will haue them receiued with more reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, becauſe they are the epiſtle of the King of heauen, written with his owne finger in the heart of the Church, (that is, the Pope, and Popiſh Prelates) whereas the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are written but with inke and paper.</p>
               <p>Theſe traditions they make of three ſorts:<note n="e" place="margin">D. Byſb. contra P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rk. de Trad.</note> 1. <hi>Diuine,</hi> deliuered by Chriſt himſelfe: 2. <hi>Apoſtolicall,</hi> deliuered by the Apoſtles: 3. <hi>Eccleſiaſticall,</hi> deliuered by the Church.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Diuine.</hi>
                  </note>1. <hi>Concerning diuine traditions</hi> (if they bee truely ſuch) we moſt reuerently and religiouſly receiue them: but wee
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:21343:25"/> acknowledge none for ſuch but onely thoſe doctrines of faith, &amp; of Gods worſhip which are either expreſly, or by neceſſary co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſequence contained in the old &amp; new Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</p>
               <p>For although we know and acknowledge that<note n="f" place="margin">Bulling. de ver. Dei.</note> the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the old Teſtament was deliuered among the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarches from hand to hand by tradition from <hi>Adam</hi> to <hi>Moſes:</hi> and of the new, till it was penned by the Apoſtles and Euangeliſts (<note n="g" place="margin">D. Abbot. cont Byſh. de Trad.</note> as ſome thinke for eight, as others for twenty, as others for foureſcore yeares:) yet wee teach that when God had taken the cuſtody of his owne traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to himſelfe by ſelecting and inſpiring choiſe veſſells of grace to commit them to writing (leaſt the ſtreames of truth ſhould haue beene polluted by running through the muddy channells of mens mouths) then the Church was bound to receiue nothing for diuine truth but what is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Scriptures, or neceſſarily deduced therefrom, and firmely grounded thereupon.</p>
               <p>As when God had conueighed the whole light of the world (<note n="h" place="margin">Gen. 1.3</note> which before was diſperſed in the firſt dayes crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) into the body of the Sunne (<note n="i" place="margin">&amp; v. 14. &amp;c.</note> created the fourth day:) then he would haue the Moone and Starres to deriue their light from thence, and the whole earth to be therewith en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightened: ſo though in his firſt plantation of his Church, God did for a time continue the knowledge of his truth by immediate reuelation thereof vnto ſome choſen men which might deliuer it to his Church from hand to hand: yet now, ſince he hath conueighed the whole light of diuine truth into the Canon of the Scripture, hee will haue all the Paſtors and members of the Church to deriue their light of ſauing knowledge and true faith from thence onely: ſo that the doctrine of the Scriptures is now the onely di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Tradition.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Touching <hi>Apoſtolicall Traditions</hi> wee acknowledge them likewiſe for diuine; if they vnderſtand thereby,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>2</hi> Apost Trad.</note> that diuine doctrine which the Apoſtles firſt preached, then wrot in the Scriptures, as the pillar and foundation of our faith: of which S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeakes,<note n="a" place="margin">Cor. 11.23.</note> 
                  <hi>Accepi a Domino quod tradidi vobis:</hi> I haue receiued of the Lord that which I haue alſo
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:21343:26"/> deliuered vnto you, &amp;c.<note n="b" place="margin">Gal. 1.11, 12.</note> for the Goſpell which was prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched of me I receiued it not of man, nor was taught it by man, but by the reuelation of Ieſus Chriſt</p>
               <p>And this is the holy and diuine Tradition which<note n="c" place="margin">Iren. li. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Irene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Cypr. Epiſt. <hi>74.</hi> &amp;c. Script. eſt.</note> 
                  <hi>Cyprian,</hi> and other auncient Fathers ſpeake of, contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Euangeliſts, Apoſtolicall Epiſtles, and Acts of the Apoſtles: (all which are written Scriptures of the new Teſtament.) This diuine and Apoſtolicall Tradition we call (with <hi>Tertullian) The rule of truth:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>1</hi> Regula veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis Tertul. <hi>2</hi> Doctrinae Cypr. <hi>3</hi> Rectitudinis. Baſil. <hi>4</hi> Credendoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; agendorum, Dyoniſ. Carthuſ.</note> and (with <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian) The rule of doctrine:</hi> (and with <hi>Baſill</hi>) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>The rule of right, or ſtraight rule of perfection:</hi> (and with their owne <hi>Carthuſian) The rule of faith and manners, or of all things to be beleeued and practiſed:</hi> for wee conſtantly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerre (with <hi>Cyril</hi>)<note n="e" place="margin">Cyril. Catech. Hieroſol.</note> 
                  <hi>That the ſecuritie of our faith ariſeth from the euidence and demonſtration of the diuine Scripture:</hi> ſo that no man preſume aboue that which is written. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6.</p>
               <p>Alſo we reuerently receiue ſuch Apoſtolicall Traditions as haue their ground in Scripture, though not expreſly<note n="f" place="margin">Act. 20.7.</note> as the celebration of the Sabboth on the firſt day of the week<note n="g" place="margin">Apoc. 1.10.</note> the Baptiſme of Infants, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>3</hi> Eccleſ. Trad.</note>3. Touching Eccleſiaſticall Traditions, wee receiue for ſuch:</p>
               <p>Firſt, thoſe doctrines of faith which the ancient Primitiue Counſailes haue determined againſt Haeretikes, hauing their ground in Scripture: as that there is a Trinitie of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in the vnitie of the diuine eſſence, and that the Sunne is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is, conſubſtantiall and coaequall with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp;c. yet we dare not ſay (with daring<note n="h" place="margin">Enchi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trov c. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Coſterius:</hi>) That the firſt foure generall Counſailes are to bee receiued as we receiue the foure Goſpells.</p>
               <p>Secondly, thoſe rules which the Primitiue Church hath ſet downe for order and comelineſſe in the ſeruice of God: yea<note n="a" place="margin">Perk. de Trad.</note> we acknowledge that the preſent Church hath power to make Canons to that purpoſe, ſo they bee conſonant to the generall Canons of the Scripture: namely 1. That they tend to<note n="b" place="margin">1 Cor. 14.26.40.</note> 
                  <hi>decency and order.</hi> 2. To <hi>aedification.</hi> 3. That they be free from ſuperſtition. 4. That the Church be not
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:21343:26"/> ouerburthened with the multitude of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Trad. Papiſt.</note>But if by the Churches Traditions they vnderſtand the Canons of their latter Counſailes (which were but conuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles or confaederacies againſt Chriſt and his truth, for the maintenance of Papall Hierarchy, and wherein all the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops were the Popes ſworne ſeruants, and directed by him as by an Oracle, what to doe, and decree: or the decrees of their Popes (ſome of which haue beene Idolatrous, ſome haereticall, and ſome ſuperſtitious:) or if vnder that name, they would thruſt vpon vs euery Fryers dreame, rotten re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques, baſe coſtome, and idle ceremony of the Romiſh Church: then we reiect their vnwritten Traditions as ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy foundations to build our faith vpon, and means to lead vs into a ſea of errors, and vncertaineties, wherein there is neither banke, nor bottome.</p>
               <p>And ſuch Traditions as theſe bee the ſandy foundations whereon they build many articles of their Romiſh Creed: namely, priuate Maſſes, halfe Communions, Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation, adoration of the hoſt of Images and reliques, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocation of Saints and Angells, Purgatory, and the Popes tranſcendent authoritie in things Eccleſiaſtical and tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall. For<note n="c" place="margin">Andrad in Orthodox Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicat. Conc. Trident. li. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> one of their owne plainly confeſſeth, That <hi>many points of their Romiſh faith would reele and totter if they were not ſupported by Traditions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this is the reaſon why they refuſe their triall by the Scriptures, and thinke<note n="d" place="margin">Conference betweene Dr. <hi>Feately,</hi> and M. <hi>Fisher.</hi>
                  </note> Chriſt and his Apoſtles, both in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>competent Iudges, and partiall witneſſes for the deciſion of their cauſe.</p>
               <p>Yea <hi>Bellarmine</hi> (their great <hi>Goliah</hi> ſaith peremptorily:)<note n="a" place="margin">Bell. li. <hi>4.</hi> de ver. dei, non ſcripto. c. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note> That it was not the proper end of the Scriptures to bee rule of our faith, and that they are at the beſt but <hi>Regula partialis non totalis:</hi> that is, a peece of a rule, but not the whole entire rule of faith. And<note n="b" place="margin">Enbhir. c. <hi>1.</hi> deſcript.</note> 
                  <hi>Coſterius</hi> affirmes, that they were not writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to that end that they ſhould preſcribe vnto vs an abſolute and exact rule of faith, and adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Sacraments, and other things neceſſary in the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Common-weale: but occaſionally to confute Iewes and Haeretikes, and to take away cer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> which
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:21343:27"/> then aroſe in the Church, and to comfort ſome that were weake, and vnſtable in the faith, &amp;c. as if the Chriſtian Church then vpon thoſe occaſions had ſome neede of the Scriptures, but now no need at all. Thus baſely (if I may not ſay blaſphemouſly) doe they thinke, ſpeake, and write of the Sacred Scriptures.</p>
               <p>And when we confute their errors out of the Scriptures, then (with the Valentinians of old) they fall to accuſe the Scriptures themſelues:<note n="c" place="margin">Iren. li. <hi>3.</hi> contra bar. c. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Quaſi non recte habeant, nec ſint ex authoritate, &amp;c. as if they were ill tranſlated, or obſcure, or imperfect without Traditions, or of no authority in themſelues without the authoritie of the Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>2</hi> Authoritas Eccleſ:</note>Therefore they make the Churches authority another maine foundation of their faith: as if it were greater than the authority of ſcripture, yea as if without that ſcripture were no ſcripture: becauſe the Church gaue teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony to the ſcriptures, that they were diuinely inſpired &amp; made them Canonicall: therefore (ſay they) both the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine, and Canonicall authority of the ſcriptures relyes vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Churches authority.</p>
               <p>But let me aske them that ſo ſay: was <hi>Iohn Baptiſts</hi> au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority greater than Chriſts, becauſe he gaue teſtimony vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him:<note n="d" place="margin">1 Ioh 29.</note> 
                  <hi>Behold the Lambe of God that taketh away the ſins of the world:</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> doth the Herald that proclaimes the Kings title and authority, giue him his title and authority? or is the gold which the goldſmith toucheth therefore good, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he (vpon trial therof by his touchſtone) declares it to be ſo? was it not ſo before his tryall? would it not haue been ſo if he had neuer tryed it? yes vndoubtedly.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Dilemma.</note>When the Church did firſt declare the ſcriptures to bee the word of God, either they were ſo before this declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Church, or not: if not, then the Church erred in declaring them to be ſo, which were blaſphemy, and flat A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſme to auerre: if they were ſo, then they receiued no diuine authority from the Churches teſtimony.</p>
               <p>I know a Ieſuit would thinke to winde himſelfe out of this dilemma with<note n="a" place="margin">Bellarm. li. <hi>2.</hi> de author. Conc. c. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Bellarmins</hi> diſtinction of <hi>in ſe, &amp; quoad nos:</hi> ſaying, that the ſcriptures are of diuine authority in
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:21343:27"/> themſelues, but could not be ſo acknowledged of vs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Churches teſtimony: but this diſtinction will not ſerue the turne: for if they bee ſo in themſelues, they would be ſo if we neuer acknowledged, or receiued them for ſuch: (as the Scriptures of the new Teſtament are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine euen among the Iewes and Turks, though they would neuer acknowledge them to be ſo:) and if they bee ſo in themſelues, why ſhould they not be ſo vnto vs? why ſhould we not receiue the ſacred Scriptures as diuine, for the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine authority which they haue in themſelues without the Churches authoritie.</p>
               <p>Indeed the Churches authority or teſtimony may bring Infidells or Haeretikes to heare the word that they may be conuerted,<note n="b" place="margin">Ioh. 1.41.45.</note> (as <hi>Andrew</hi> brought <hi>Peter,</hi> or <hi>Philip, Natha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel</hi> vnto Chriſt, or as the woman of Samaria brought the citizens of Samaria to heare Chriſt with her teſtimony of him:<note n="c" place="margin">c. 4, 39.</note> 
                  <hi>Come ſee a man which hath told me all that euer J did: Is not he the Chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And in this ſenſe is that S. <hi>Aug.</hi> ſaith:<note n="d" place="margin">Aug. cont. epiſt fundamenti c. <hi>5</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>I ſhould not haue beleeued the Goſpell, if the authority of the Church had not mooued me thereunto:</hi> but when they haue heard it, they are conuerted, and beleeue, not for the Churches teſtimony, but by the diuine authority, and coeleſtiall efficacy of the word it ſelfe, which is<note n="e" place="margin">Rom. 1.16.</note> 
                  <hi>The power of God vnto ſaluation to eueryone that beleeueth:</hi> as the Samaritans ſaid to the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man:<note n="f" place="margin">Ioh. 4.2.</note> 
                  <hi>Now we beleeue not becauſe of thy words, for wee haue heard him our ſelues, and know that this is indeed the Chriſt, the Sauiour of the world.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>3.</hi> Jnfallibilitas Papae.</note>The third ſandy foundation of the Romiſh faith is the <hi>Popes infallibility:</hi> which I doe not falſely impoſe vpon them as a generall ground of their faith, (though ſome of their owne learned men hold the contrary: becauſe their grand champion <hi>Bellarmine</hi> auerres, and prooues that it is<note n="g" place="margin">Bellarm. de Rom. Pom. li. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Communiſsima opinio fere omnium Catholicorum:</hi> that is, <hi>the moſt common and generall tenet of all thoſe of the Church of Rome, whom he calls Catholikes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For although the Papiſts brag much of their Catholike Church that it can teach nothing but Catholike truth:
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:21343:28"/> and is not ſubiect vnto error, becauſe Chriſt ſaid of his true Church built vpon him and the rocke of his diuine truth,<note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 16.11.</note> 
                  <hi>That the gates of hell ſhould not preuaile againſt it:</hi> which they falſely apply to the Church of Rome:<note n="b" place="margin">Rom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.8.</note> whoſe faith was indeed once famous through the world, though now the<note n="c" place="margin">Eſa. 21, 22.</note> 
                  <hi>faithfull city be become an harlot,</hi> her gold mixed with droſſe, and her wine with water: yet aske them what they meane by that Church that cannot erre, they will tell you they meane thereby the Pope (the head of the Church, and Saint <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſsor)<note n="d" place="margin">Luc. 22.32.</note> for whoſe faith Chriſt pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that it ſhould not faile.</p>
               <p>So <hi>Bellarmine</hi> affirmeth, That the common opinion of Romiſh Catholikes is<note n="e" place="margin">Bellar. ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>Ipſam infallibilitatem non eſſe in coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu Conciliorum, vt in concilio Epiſcoporum, ſed in ſolo Pontifice:</hi> that the infallibilitie reſts not in the aſſembly of Counſailes, nor in the counſell of Biſhops, but in the Pope alone: for they hold that any member or Paſtor of their Church is ſubiect vnto error: yea all the Biſhops and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors of the Church aſſembled in a generall Counſaile (if the Pope confirme not their Canons:) onely the Pope can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not erre when he defines a matter of faith, <hi>Ex Cathedra,</hi> (that is, by his Papall authority,) as if the Popes chayre were made of Iriſh wood, to which no cobweb of errour could poſsibly cleaue.</p>
               <p>And therefore all muſt be Haeretikes that be not within his pale, ſcripture muſt be no ſcripture without his allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and Kings no Kings if he pleaſe to kick their crowns of their heads with his holineſſe foot, or to bellow out ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communications, and depoſitions againſt them with his Papall Bull. Yea hee may make new articles of faith: (as <hi>Pius quartus</hi> did adde twelue articles to the Nicene Creed in a Bull of his (ſent out about the time of her <hi>Tridentine conuenticle</hi>) entitled<note n="f" place="margin">Bulla Pii <hi>4</hi> ſuper formae profeſſ. fidei.</note> 
                  <hi>The publike profeſsion of the Orthodox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all faith to be vniformely profeſſed and obſerued:</hi> and likewiſe he may adde ten commandements of the Church to the ten commandements of Almighty God (which I haue ſeene in an Engliſh Roman Catechiſme:) which muſt be kept with all Religious obedience of all the Popes Diſciples: and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:21343:28"/> againſt the commandements of God, by allowing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtuous marriages, and the religious vowes of children made without the conſent, yea againſt the will of their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, and the depoſing and murthering of Princes for the aduancement of the Catholike Religion.</p>
               <p>Theſe be ſtrange concluſions to be drawne from Chriſts prayer for <hi>Peter</hi> that his faith ſhould not faile: which place<note n="a" place="margin">Aug. de cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rept. &amp; gra. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note> S. <hi>Aug.</hi> will haue to be meant onely of <hi>Peters</hi> own particular ſauing faith, whereby he ſhould after his fall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt the temptations of Sathan, and ſtand faſt vnto aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life: and comfort and ſtrengthen his brethren (falling as he did) with the ſame comforts wherewith himſelfe was comforted of God: which expoſition ſeemes moſt conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to the ſcope of the text. But admit it to be meant of that <hi>doctrine of faith</hi> which S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſhould teach the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Church: ſhall they therfore deriue the effect of Chriſts prayer from <hi>Peter</hi> to the Popes of Rome, from an holy A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle (diuinely inſpired, and directed by Gods vnerring ſpirit into all truth,<note n="b" place="margin">Ioh. 16.13.</note> according to Chriſts promiſe made to his Apoſtles:) to a ranke and ſucceſsion of men among whom their owne Hiſtories do teſtifie that there haue been found Atheiſts, Infidells, Idolaters, Heretikes, Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes, incarnate diuells, and hatefull monſters of mankind? vndoubtedly ſo good praemiſes will ill beare ſo bad conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Jnſt. </seg>
                  </label> I need not goe farre for inſtances, their owne hiſtories afford ſuch plenty.<note n="c" place="margin">Baron. Annal. Anno. <hi>3033.</hi>
                  </note> 1. <hi>Marcellin.</hi> turned Pagan, and ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed to heatheniſh Idols: for which hee was condemned in the counſaile of <hi>Sinueſſa.</hi> 2.<note n="d" place="margin">Idem. An. <hi>357.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Liberius</hi> was an Arrian, and ſubſcribed to the vniuſt condemnation of <hi>Athanaſius.</hi> 3. <hi>Honorius</hi> was a <hi>Monothelite</hi> (holding that Chriſt had but one will, &amp; conſequently but one nature:) for which he was condemned in<note n="e" place="margin">Synod. <hi>6.</hi> act. <hi>4.12, 13.</hi> &amp; <hi>7.</hi> act. vlt. &amp; <hi>8.</hi> &amp; act. <hi>7.</hi>
                  </note> three ſeuerall counſailes. 4.<note n="f" place="margin">Theod Niem. de ſchiſm. li. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>44.</hi>
                  </note> The counſailes of Piſa and Conſtance condemned <hi>Greg.</hi> 12. and <hi>Benedict</hi> 13. for notorious Schiſmatikes, obſtinate Haeretikes, ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalizers of the whhle Church, and vnworthy, the Papacy. 5.<note n="g" place="margin">&amp; Conc. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtan. <hi>5.73.</hi> Bin. Com. Conc. P. <hi>1584.</hi>
                  </note> And the ſame Counſaile of Conſtance condemned <hi>Iohn</hi> the twenty three for an Atheiſt, becauſe he held as his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:21343:29"/> that there was no immortality of the ſoule, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the body, nor life euerlaſting. 6.<note n="h" place="margin">Conc. Baſill. ſect. <hi>34.</hi>
                  </note> The coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile of <hi>Baſill</hi> depoſed <hi>Eugenius</hi> the fourth, declaring him to be a Simoniſt, a periured wretch, an incorrigible ſchiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike, and an obſtinate haeretike.</p>
               <p>And<note n="a" place="margin">Watſon quod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bet.</note> 
                  <hi>Bellarmine</hi> being demanded after the death of <hi>Sixtus</hi> 5. what hee thought became of him, anſwered: <hi>Quantum capio, quantum ſapio, quantum intelligo, deſcendit ad infernum.</hi> As farre as I can thinke, conceiue, or vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, he is gone directly vnto hell.</p>
               <p>It is ſtrange therefore that thoſe that haue no faith themſelues ſhould be ſuch infallible rules to guide the faith of others, and to lead others to heauen while themſelues goe to hell: (ſeeing no norme or ſquire can make other things ſquared thereby ſtraight lf it ſelfe be crooked, nor any man iudicially determine otherwiſe than himſelfe iudgeth) vnleſſe there be ſuch a vertue annexed to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall chaire that (be the Pope what he will) when hee ſits downe therein, he ſhall be like<note n="b" place="margin">Num. 23.11.</note> 
                  <hi>Balaam</hi> to bleſſe where he meanes to curſe, or like<note n="c" place="margin">Ioh. 11.50.51.</note> 
                  <hi>Caiaphas</hi> to prophecye and ſpeake truth, not vnderſtanding what he ſaith.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Dr. <hi>Field</hi> of the Church. <hi>li.</hi> 3. <hi>in Append.</hi>
                  </note>Moreouer, it is the iudgement of many of their owne di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines, (namely, <hi>Bozius, Gerſon, Occam, Almaine, Alphon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus a Caſtro,</hi> and the <hi>Sorboniſts:</hi>) that the Pope may not onely be an Haeretike himſelfe, but write, teach, preach, and define Haereſie, and that <hi>è Cathedra: (.i.</hi> by his Papall au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority.) And diuers inſtances are giuen by our<note n="e" place="margin">Dr. <hi>VVhite</hi> of the Church. <hi>ſect</hi> 36.</note> learned Diuines wherein they haue actually erred not onely in Church Canons, diſpenſations, and Papall decrees, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in matters of faith defined by them both in Prouinciall and generall Counſailes. And one of their owne Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts ſaith<note n="f" place="margin">Apud Grat. D. <hi>4.</hi> Si Papa.</note> That <hi>if the Pope be found ſo negligent of his owne and his brethrens ſaluation that he draw innumerable ſoules by troopes with himſelfe to be damned in hell, no man may ſay vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, why doeſt thou ſo?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What a lamentable thing is this, that poore ſeduced ſoules ſhould thus forſake the rocke of truth to build their faith on ſuch ſandy foundations; namely, the Churches
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:21343:29"/> Traditions, as they are deliuered by the Pope and the Churches authoritie, which is in effect nothing els but the Popes infallibility: (who is the Church<note n="g" place="margin">Greg. de Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentia. T. <hi>3.</hi> diſp. <hi>1.</hi> P. <hi>24.</hi>
                  </note> virtually, becauſe all the power of the Church reſts wholy in him:) and yet he a man that may be, and often hath beene an obſtinate Haeretike, Schiſmatike, Atheiſt, &amp;c. and teach, preach, and define error, and lead thouſands with himſelfe headlong vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hell.</p>
               <p>But let vs renounce ſuch ſandy foundations, and build our faith on the rocke of truth, contained in the Scripture: for the ſacred Scripture is that<note n="a" place="margin">Zanc. de ſcrip.</note> 
                  <hi>Paradiſe of God,</hi> in the midſt whereof are: firſt, <hi>the tree of knowledge,</hi> bearing no forbidden fruit: for<note n="b" place="margin">Deut. 29.29.</note> 
                  <hi>reuealed things are for vs and our chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly,<note n="c" place="margin">Apoc. 2.7.</note> 
                  <hi>The tree of life</hi> (Chriſt Ieſus, the kernell and pith of the ſcriptures:) and no<note n="d" place="margin">Gen. 3. vlt.</note> Cherubin ſet with a fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming ſword to keepe vs from it: but the way left wide o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, and all inuited to come vnto it:<note n="e" place="margin">Mat. 11.28.</note> 
                  <hi>Come vnto me, &amp;c.</hi> Thirdly,<note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 23.2.</note> 
                  <hi>Riuers of liuing waters</hi> to refreſh and comfort our ſoules in temptation, affliction, and perſecution.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, A coeleſtiall aire ſweetly breathing in the midſt thereof: (<hi>videlicet,</hi>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">2. Tim. 3.16.</note> 
                  <hi>afflatus Spiritus Sancti,</hi> the inſpirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the holy Ghoſt,) inſpiring both the penmen of it, and all that with faith, humility, and reuerence, reade or heare it.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, God walking in the midſt of this Eden: whoſe voice doth teach, reprooue, correct, inſtruct, and comfort euery ſonne of <hi>Adam,</hi> that doth heare, and doe it, making him<note n="h" place="margin">V. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>wiſe vnto ſaluation through the faith that is in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. A ſecond ſort of thoſe that build on the ſand are Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane ſinners: who build on the ſand of their owne ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and praeſumption of Gods mercy,<note n="i" place="margin">Rom. 6.11.</note> 
                  <hi>continuing in ſinne that grace may abound,</hi> as if God were wholy compoſed of mercy. This perſuaſion giues encouragement to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane ſwearer to flye in the face of God, and threaten hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen with his blaſphemies, as if he would <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, fight with God, and dare him to put on his habergion of iuſtice,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:21343:30"/> and gird himſelfe with his ſword of vengeance: ſaying in his heart,<note n="k" place="margin">Mal. 2.17.</note> 
                  <hi>Where is the God of iudgement?</hi> And to the ſwi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh drunkard, and laſciuious adulterer to ouerburthen the earth with their impieties,<note n="l" place="margin">Eph. 4.19.</note> 
                  <hi>turning the grace of God into wantonneſſe, and committing all vncleanneſſe euen with gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines:</hi> and yet ſay in their hearts,<note n="m" place="margin">Pſal. 10, 11.</note> 
                  <hi>Tuſh, God hath forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, he hideth his face and will neuer ſee it.</hi> (As if that God that made both day and night, and to whom<note n="n" place="margin">Pſal. 239.12</note> 
                  <hi>the night is as cleare as the day</hi>) did not as well behold the one walking ſecretly in the twilight,<note n="o" place="margin">Pro. 7.9.</note> as the other impudently ſtaggering in the ſtreetes at no one day.</p>
               <p>But thoſe ſhall one day know that the<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 116.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord is righteous as well as gratious:</hi> and hath not onely his throane of grace, but his ſeat for iudgement.<note n="b" place="margin">Apoc. 4.3.</note> As there is a rainebow about his throane in ſight like vnto an <hi>Emerald</hi> (repreſenting his mercy, and couenant of grace, which is euer greene and freſh, and moſt comfortable to his children, and whence he continually ſtreames downe ſhowers of ſpirituall and temporall bleſsings vpon them: ſo out of this throane proceed<note n="c" place="margin">v. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>lightnings, and thunderings, and voyces,</hi> to ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie his iudgements denounced againſt, and reſerued for the wicked.<note n="d" place="margin">Cypr. de Lapſ.</note> 
                  <hi>Deus enim quantum patris pietate indulgens ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per &amp; bonus eſt, ita iudicis maieſtate metuendus, &amp;c.</hi> For God as he hath the tender indulgence of a father, ſo hath he the dreadfull maieſtie of a iudge he hath prepared both heauen and hell, as well places of aeternall ſorrow and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as ioy and ſolace; and as well the pit of infernall darkeneſſe as the light that no mortall man can attaine un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to.</p>
               <p>Let the Prophane ſinner therefore know for a ſurety, that if he<note n="e" place="margin">Leu. 26.21 24.</note> walke contrary to God (by iniquity, and obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy) God will walke contrary to him in wrath and fury. If he prouoke God dayly by curſing and ſwearing, God will ſend out a<note n="f" place="margin">Zach 5.1.2. &amp;c,</note> flying roule of curſes againſt him, that ſhall flye into the midſt of his houſe and conſume it with the timber and ſtones thereof. If he drinke without thirſt. and waſtfully ſwallow downe flagons of wine here: hee ſhall thirſt without drinke, and not haue a<note n="g" place="margin">Luc. 16.24.</note> droppe of cold water to coole his tongue hereafter. And if he burne with
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:21343:30"/> the fire of vnlawfull luſt here, he ſhall (without ſerious and ſeaſonable repentance,) burne hereafter in the<note n="h" place="margin">Apoc. 21.8.</note> lake that burnes with fire and brimſtone for euer: for the Lord doth as well treaſure vp wrath f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r the<note n="i" place="margin">Rom. 9 22 23</note> veſſells of wrath, as mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy for the veſſells of mercy,<note n="k" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ireen. li</hi> 3. c 43.</note> 
                  <hi>Saluat ſaluandos, &amp; iudicat iudicio dignos, &amp;c.</hi> He ſaues thoſe that are to be ſaued, and condemnes thoſe that are worthy to be damned, making the one a receptacle of his mercy and an organe of ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the other a receptacle of iudgement, and organe of damnation.</p>
               <p n="3">3. A third ſort are couetous Mammoniſts: who build their neſts in this world: beeing herein more fooliſh than the ſwallowe<note n="a" place="margin">Solinus,</note> that will not build her neſt in a ruinous houſe: for the world is a great houſe whoſe whole fabricke ſhall fall to ruine,<note n="b" place="margin">2 Pet. 3.10.</note> 
                  <hi>The heauens ſhall vaniſh as a ſcrowle, the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſhall melt with heat, and the earth with all therein ſhall be burnt vp.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe are rightly ſaide to build on the ſand: for the world and worldly things are like the ſand in two re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Quia flaida:</hi> becauſe all things therein flowe and floate like a quickeſand:<note n="c" place="margin">1 Ioh. 2.17.</note> for <hi>the world paſſeth away and the luſts thereof.</hi> Whence it is compared to a<note n="d" place="margin">Apoc. 4.6.</note> Sea of glaſſe: To a ſea, becauſe it ebbes, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d flowes, and is tempeſtuous: and to a glaſsie ſea, becauſe all things therein are brittle and ſlippery, ſliding, fading, vaniſhing in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Quia ſterilia:</hi> As ſand is barraine, ſo worldly things (eſpecially if couetouſly affected, vniuſtly gotten and baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly poſſeſſed) are fruitleſſe, and vnprofitable<note n="e" place="margin">Pro 10.2, 3.</note> Treaſures of wickedneſſe profit nothing, for the Lord caſteth away the ſubſtance of the wicked.</p>
               <p>Therefore, though the world account her darlings O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles of wiſedome, yet in Gods Dictionary they be tear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med fooles:<note n="f" place="margin">Lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 12.20.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou foole, this night will they take away thy ſoule, &amp;c.</hi> The word is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, (ſignifying <hi>improuident,</hi>) for though worldlings be ſo wiſe<note n="g" place="margin">Mat. 16.26.</note> to win the world, yet they are ſo improuident to looſe their owne ſoules. And
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:21343:31"/> marke I pray you how many points of extreame folly they commit.</p>
               <p n="1">1. They doe with great care and paines gather that which they cannot long enioy: but it ſhall bee taken from them, or they from it in a moment.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They lay vp their treaſure where all their Praedeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors haue loſt it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They make their ſeruant their maſter: that is, ſerue <hi>Mammon</hi> which ſhould ſerue them.</p>
               <p n="4">4.<note n="h" place="margin">1 Tim. 6.9, 10</note> They pierce themſelues thorow with many ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes.</p>
               <p n="5">5. They preferre (which is the greateſt folly) gold be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, gaine before godlineſſe, money before mercy, the world before their owne ſoules: and that when they are neereſt their graue, and ſo drowne themſelues irrecoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably inperdition and deſtruction.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Applicat. </seg>1:</label> 1. O that euery oppreſsing <hi>Ahab</hi> would think of this, that is<note n="a" place="margin">1 Reg. 21.4.</note> ſicke for <hi>Naboths</hi> vineyard, and neuer weary<note n="b" place="margin">Eſa. 5.8.</note> ioyning houſe to houſe, and land to land, till there be no roome for the poore in the earth: for certainely hee that builds his houſe as the<note n="c" place="margin">Iob 27.18.</note> moth, (that is, by ſpoiling and conſuming o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers)<note n="d" place="margin">Eſa. 53.1.</note> when he ſhall ceaſe to ſpoile, ſhall himſelfe be ſpoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and conſumed.</p>
               <p>This is the cauſe of the dec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y of ſo many great families both in city and countrey, becauſe they haue built their houſes not onely vainly on the ſand, but cruelly in an <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheldama, a field of bloud: for</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>Syrac.</hi> 34.21.</note> 
                  <hi>the bread of the needy is the life of the poore, he that robs him thereof is a murtherer.</hi> If houſes therefore be thus built (though neuer ſo high) <hi>the</hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">Hab. 2.11, 12.</note> 
                  <hi>ſtone out of the wall ſhall cry, and the beame of the timber ſhall anſwer it, woe to him that buildeth his houſe with bloud, and erecteth a city by iniquity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. O that euery Symoniacal Patron, and greedy Impropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator would thinke of this, that robs God to inrich him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. (<note n="g" place="margin">Mal. 3, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>ye haue robbed me in tythes, and offerings, &amp;c.</hi>) and (like the Eagle) with the fleſh that he takes from Gods al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, carries a coale to burne his owne neſt.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:21343:31"/>3. O that euery vnconſcionable Lawyer would thinke of this: who if he put not on the Lyons skinne, will put on the Foxes caſe, and get by cunning vnder praetence of Lawe what hee cannot get by violence. I taxe not you (Reuerend Fathers of the Lawe) I doubt not but you account Godlineſſe your greateſt Gaine, and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing euery man right your greateſt ioy: for that will build you ſure houſes, and bring you peace at the laſt.</p>
               <p>But let me beſeech you in the bowells of Chriſt, not to ſuffer thoſe that are vnder you to delay cauſes ſo long till the ſilly ſheepe that goes to lawe for a locke of his wooll loſt in the countrey, looſe his whole fleece in the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty before hee end his ſuit: for it is a common com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint among vs poore Countrey-men, that a poore man were better giue away his coate than goe to lawe for it againſt a rich aduerſary: for let his cauſe bee neuer ſo iuſt, and honeſt, if his Aduerſaries purſe be ſtronger, he ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer haue an end of it, till he hath ſpent himſelfe, and loſt his cauſe.</p>
               <p n="4">4. O that griping Vſurers would thinke of this, that ſecretly eate vp mens eſtates, as the Moth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumes a garment, or little wormes the heart of a great Oake. Though this ſinne may pleade praeſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, (becauſe the roote thereof is couetouſneſſe: which is as auncient as the fall of man, and the<note n="a" place="margin">1 Tim. 6.10.</note> roote of all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill) yet<note n="b" place="margin">D. <hi>Fenton</hi> of Vſurie.</note> a learned Diuine (late of this Church and Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) in a treatiſe of his againſt this ſinne of Vſurie, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerres and prooues ſubſtantially, That neuer any Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Church Orthodoxall, or Haereticall, defended it as lawfull (as it is now practiſed among vs) fince the world ſtood,</p>
               <p>How then doeſt thou hope to dye a Chriſtian, if thou liue and dye an Vſurer, which no Chriſtian Church did euer approoue? If it bee a condition required of him that will<note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>5.</note> enter into Gods Tabernacle, that he lend not his money vpon vſurie, how doeſt thou then
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:21343:32"/> that makeſt it thy trade, and doeſt liue, and dye, in it hope to enter?</p>
               <p>If euer therefore thou looke for remiſsion of thy ſinnes at the hands of God, and ſaluation of thy ſoule, repent ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily, and make reſtitution: It is the poſition of that iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and learned Father S. <hi>Aug.</hi> concerning euery ſinne of this nature, wherein our brother is really wronged by impairing his eſtate to increaſe ours vnlawfully:<note n="d" place="margin">Aug. epiſt. <hi>54.</hi> ad Macedon.</note> 
                  <hi>Non re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittitur peccatum, niſi reſtituatur ablatum reſtitui poteſt. .i.</hi> The ſinne is not remitted by God, vnleſſe that which is wrongfully taken from our brother be reſtored, if a man be able to make reſtitution: for God will neuer forgiue, nor receiue vs ſo long as wee vniuſtly retaine what is none of ours. I know this is <hi>Colloguintida</hi> to the vſurers heart, but he muſt ſwallow this bitter pill, if euer he will bee purged from his finne.</p>
               <p>But I ſpend too much time vpon thoſe that<note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. 51.17.</note> hate to bee reformed: and haue ſtopped their eares (like deafe Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders) at the voices of better charmers: for one ſaith true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of an Vſurer: <hi>Poenitet expenſi praeterea nihili:</hi> Hee neuer repents of any thing but of his coſt and expences: Yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing called to this place (which is reported to be the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Mart for this ſinnefull trade) I could not but ſpeake ſomething thereof: it may pleaſe God for the conuerſion of ſome: (for hee doth manifeſt his power in weakeneſſe, and<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 8.2.</note> out of the mouths of Babes and Sucklings hath ordei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſtrength:) if not, yet for the diſcharge of mind, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and deliuerance of mine owne ſoule.</p>
               <p n="5">5. O that the couetous Merchant would conſider this, that doth engroſſe commodities that he may haue <hi>Monopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies,</hi> (that is, none ſell but he, and ſo ſell at his owne rates:) whereby he doth grind the faces of the poore Tradeſmen, and eate out the bowells of poore buyers, that ſtand in need of ſuch commodities And the deceitfull artificer or Tradeſ-man: for now ſingle trades are growne to be dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and in one trade or occupation there be two skills: the one of doing it truely, the other of doing it deceitfully:
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:21343:32"/> called the myſtery of the trade, which for the moſt part is a myſtery of iniquity:) for now hee that knowes the fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhood as well as the truth of his trade, and can ſet a good glaſſe vpon bad wares, is the moſt skilfull tradeſman; and he that can make an excellent counterfeit, and ſell it for good, and at as great a price, is accounted the beſt artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer. Thus men take money not for wares but for coſenage, and ſelling deceit, doe buy with the price thereof (if they ſpeedily repent not) their owne moſt certaine damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>Thus you ſee into how many intricate mazes, <hi>Mammon</hi> doth leade men to their owne deſtruction: Bee not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſlaues of Mammon, leaſt ye become the proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries of hell and damnation: for as pride ſhut vp hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen againſt the diuell, and gluttony Paradiſe againſt our firſt parents: ſo couetouſneſſe is the key to open hell gates to the ſeruants of Mammon. If therefore thou wouldeſt ſhunne the<note n="b" place="margin">Mat. 7.13, 14.</note> broad way and open gate to deſtruction, and find the narrow way and ſtreight gate that leades to ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. S. <hi>Bernard</hi> teacheth thee how to doe it,<note n="c" place="margin">Ber. in Cant. ſect <hi>35.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Jnueniſti plane ſapientiae viam, ſi prioris vitae peccata defleas, ſi huius ſaeculi deſiderabilia parui-pendas, ſi bona opera exerceas, &amp; ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternam beatitudinem toto deſiderio concupiſcas.</hi> Thou haſt found the way of wiſedome, if thou bewaile thy ſinnes, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne the worlds vanities, exerciſe thy ſelfe in good works, and earneſtly mind and deſire heauenly happineſſe.</p>
               <p n="4">4. A fourth ſort of theſe fooliſh builders on the ſand, are masqued Hypocrites: who build their praeſuming hope and confidence of their ſaluation, vpon the ſandy foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their fained holineſſe: for they haue<note n="a" place="margin">2 Tim 3.5.</note> 
                  <hi>forme of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe but deny the power thereof.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe (as a<note n="b" place="margin">D. <hi>Boyce</hi> Deane of Cant. in his <hi>Poſtill.</hi>
                  </note> Reuerend and learned Diuine of our Church hath well obſerued) doe mocke God and the world.</p>
               <p n="1">1. They mocke God and his word, for where God ſaith, <hi>Facite iuſtitiam,</hi> worke righteouſneſſe, they doe, <hi>non facere, ſed fingere,</hi> not doe, but faine righteouſneſſe:<note n="c" place="margin">Mat. 23.25.</note> making cleane the outſide of the cuppe and the platter, but within
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:21343:33"/> are full of rottenneſſe and corruption.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They deceiue men being Chriſtians in lippe onely, not in life: making a maſque of Religion: or rather a very vizar, with eyes, noſe, and mouth fairely proportioned to all purpoſes.</p>
               <p>For they will flocke and flye to the temples (as doues to the windowes) and lift vp the white of the eyes, and ſit at the Preachers feet (as<note n="d" place="margin">Luc. 10.19.</note> 
                  <hi>Mary</hi> at Chriſts) and ſend out whole vollyes of ſighes when the word is preached,<note n="e" place="margin">Lact. Inſtitut. l. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>20.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Sed omnem religionem in templo, &amp; cum templo relinquunt, &amp;c.</hi> They leaue all their Religion at the Church, and carry none home with them to expreſſe it in their liues.</p>
               <p>If ye deale with them, ye ſhall finde<note n="f" place="margin">Gen, 27.22.</note> 
                  <hi>Iacobs ſmooth voice,</hi> but <hi>Eſaus</hi> rough hands: for the Hypocrite is like counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit gold, faire in ſhew, but falſe in touch: <hi>Intus Nero, foris Cato, totus ambiguus:</hi> a <hi>Cato</hi> for his outward grauity, but a <hi>Nero</hi> for his inward malice and crueltie, <hi>a meere aequiuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator:</hi>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">Cypr. Ep <hi>54.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Aliud enim corde occultat, aliud voce pronunciat:</hi> He ſpeakes one thing, and meanes another.</p>
               <p>But moſt of all hee deceiues his owne ſoule building on the ſand while he thinkes he builds on the rock, &amp; ſo builds his owne ruine: for when the flouds of perſecution ariſe, they ſoo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e waſh away his painted holineſſe, and caſt downe his rotten building: and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fall therof is great euen to the bottome of hell: which is the hypocrites proper portion, and haereditary poſſeſsion, wherein all other ſinners doe but ſhare with him:<note n="h" place="margin">Mat. 24.51.</note> 
                  <hi>They ſhall haue their portion with hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>Pars. <hi>3.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The third difference betweene theſe wiſe and fooliſh builders, is in the effect or iſſue of their building: which in the one is firme ſtabilitie <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, If fell not, and in the other, a ſuddaine and fearefull ruine. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>And it fell, and the fall thereof was great.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <note place="margin">v. 25.</note>1. In the former are implyed three things. 1. <hi>Tenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio varia: The varietie of the temptations, And the raine fell, &amp;c.</hi> 2. <hi>Tentationum victoria:</hi> The victory that this firme building had ouer theſe temptations: in that (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all theſe) it ſtood faſt and immooueable, and
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:21343:33"/> could not be caſt downe. <hi>(And it fell not:)</hi> 3. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ictoria cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa:</hi> The cauſe of this victory, and impregnable ſtability: becauſe it was built on a rocke.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In the latter are likewiſe implyed 3. things: 1. <hi>Ruinae cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa:</hi> The cauſe of the ruine: <hi>And the raine fell,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">v. 27.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c. and beat vpon that houſe:</hi> 2. <hi>Ruina ipſa:</hi> The ruine it ſelfe: <hi>And it fell.</hi> 3. <hi>Ruinae qualitas ſeu natura:</hi> The nature or qualitie of that ruine: <hi>And the fall thereof was great.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1.</hi> Tent. varia</note> The ten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ations that aſſaile both theſe buildings are the ſame, wherein obſerue: 1. <hi>Tent. numerum,</hi> their number or diuerſity: (<hi>viz.</hi> raine, flouds, winde.) 2. <hi>Impetum:</hi> their forcible nature, and violence: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>They beate vpon that houſe.</hi> For theſe three (raine, flouds, and windes) aſſaile a materiall houſe on euery ſide to try whether the building be firme or no: 1. The raine beates vpon the roofe of the houſe. 2. The flouds vndermine the foundation: 3. The winds beat on the walls and ſides of the houſe: as that<note n="a" place="margin">Iob 1.15</note> whirle-wind did ſmite the foure corners of <hi>Iobs</hi> houſe, and threw it flat to the ground.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Expoſit. </seg>
                  </label> I will not trouble you with the varietie of opinions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Interpretors, what is here myſtically meant by raine, flouds, and winds: I take it Chriſt meanes hereby to include all kinds of temptations, wherewith the Chriſtian Church in generall, and euery Chriſtian ſoule in particular is aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulted, and violently beat vpon by the world, fleſh, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, to ouerthrow it and bring it to ruine.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Pluuia.</hi>
                  </note>But if ye will haue a difference made betweene them, I thinke 1. By the raine is meant the temptation of proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: which ſoftens mens minds ouermuch with wantonnes and luxury, and ſo workes their ruine: for raine falls <hi>gut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatim,</hi> by droppes, and ſoakes into the houſe by little and little, and ſo rots the rafters and beames, and brings it to ruine.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <note place="margin">2. <hi>Flumina.</hi>
                  </note>2. By the flouds are meant the <hi>Tentations of aduerſitie, (.i.</hi> afflictions and perſecutions:) which like <hi>Torrents</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile this building violently to ouerturne it from the very foundation: for afflictions are called flouds in Scripture.<note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. 69.2.</note> I am come into great waters where the flouds ouerthrow
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:21343:34"/> me <hi rend="sup">b</hi> And perſecutions alſo: <hi>The flouds of vngodly men made me afraid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <note place="margin">3. <hi>Venti.</hi>
                  </note>3. By the windes are meant the <hi>tentations of perſuaſion,</hi> whereby Sathan and his inſtruments (which like <hi>Elymas</hi> the ſorcerer are<note n="c" place="margin">Act. 13.10.</note> full of all ſubtletie and miſchiefe, and ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of all righteouſneſſe) ceaſe not to peruert (as much as in them lyes) the ſtraight wayes of the Lord.</p>
               <p>And this they ſeeke to doe two wayes.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Per blanditias, .i.</hi> By their ſubtle perſuaſions and faire allurements: for (as S. <hi>Gregory</hi> ſaith,<note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Greg. mor. li.</hi> 3. c. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>Verba molliunt dum virus infundunt:</hi> that is, (to vſe the phraſe of the Pſal.)<note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. 55.21.</note> 
                  <hi>Their words be ſmoother then oyle, yet they be very ſwords:</hi> namely, to pierce, wound, and kill mens ſoules. Theſe may bee compared to the warme Southwindes, or plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Weſtwinds: which (with their warme, but ſtrong blaſts) may ouerthrow an houſe as ſoone as the bluſtering Northwinds.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Per minas, .i.</hi> Their cruell threatnings, and bloudy inquiſitions whereby they endeauour to deterre men from truth, and force them to entertaine error for feare, if not for loue: and when they cannot perſuade, they will enforce mens conſciences. Theſe may be compared to that<note n="f" place="margin">Ion 1.4.</note> 
                  <hi>ſtormie wind</hi> raiſed vpon the ſea, when <hi>Ionas</hi> was in the ſhip: or S. <hi>Pauls</hi> tempeſtuous wind (called<note n="g" place="margin">Act. 27, 14, 15</note> 
                  <hi>Euroclydon</hi>) which draue his ſhip with ſuch violence, that the Mariners could not guide it, but were faine to let it driue whither it would.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctr. </seg>
                  </label> The true Church and euery member thereof is aſſailed &amp; tryed on euery ſide: In peaceable times with the raine of proſperity, and warme ſouthwinds of haereticall ſuggeſtions: and in troubleſome times with the blu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tering Northwinds of tyrannicall th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eatnings, and violent torrents of p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. In the one the Church is<note n="a" place="margin">Cypr. de Lap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Militum Chriſti cohors can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dida</hi> the white band of Chriſts ſouldiers, fighting vnder the white enſigne of peace: in the other <hi>rubicunda</hi> the blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy band, fighting vnder the bloudy banners of perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: for ſometimes, the <hi>P. of peace</hi> holds out the <hi>white flag of peace</hi> to his Church: ſometime, the L. of Hoſts holds out vnto her the <hi>bloudy ſtreamer of warre bloudſhed, and perſecution,</hi> and tries
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:21343:34"/> as well by the one as the other, whether his ſouldiers will cleaue cloſe to their captaine, and follow their coulers.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>1</hi> Tent. proſper.</note>1. Smooth<note n="b" place="margin">Gen. 27.22.36.</note> 
                  <hi>Jacob</hi> (the worlds faire ſonne) proſperitie may as ſoone and ſooner deceiue and ſupplant vs, than rough <hi>Eſau</hi> (the worlds churliſh ſonne) affliction and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution: for the poyſon of aduerſitie is ſometimes ſo tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered in our ſoules with the wholeſome ingredients of faith, hope, patience, and humilitie, that in ſtead of killing it doth cure vs, and purge our ſoules of the corrupt humors of ſinne: and ſo playes the ſchoolemaſter, not onely in whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping and ſcourging vs, but alſo in teaching and inſtructing vs to know God, and our ſelues, and the worlds vanitie, and to labour after a more permanent faelicity. Whereas proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peritie many times (like<note n="c" place="margin">Iud. 16, 19, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0.</note> 
                  <hi>Dalila</hi>) lulls many a ſtrong <hi>Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> ſo long aſleepe in her lappe of carnall pleaſures that ſhe takes from him that wherein his ſpirituall ſtrength con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth, and betrayes him to that vncircumciſed Philiſtim the diuell.</p>
               <p>So then the worlds muſicke of profits and pleaſures is but a <hi>Syrens ſong,</hi> which while it tickles our eares, it wounds our hearts, and ſplits our ſoules vpon the rockes of ſinne, whereby ofttimes wee make ſhippe-wracke of our ſaluation,<note n="d" place="margin">2 Sam 11.2. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Dauid</hi> who did cleaue faſt vnto God in his troubles, in his proſperitie ſtarted aſide like a broken bow, and fell into the fearefull ſinnes of Adultery and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Peter</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 26.51. &amp; Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 18.10 18</note> who ſtoutly defended his maſter among the ſwords and ſtaues in the garden, baſely denyed him, when he was baſting himſelfe by the fire in the high Prieſts hall.<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug.</hi> in Pſal. 34.</note> 
                  <hi>Homo victus in Paradiſo, victor in ſtercore,</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Ioq 2.8.</note> 
                  <hi>Job</hi> by his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience was a conquerour on the dunghill, and<note n="d" place="margin">Gen. 3.6.</note> 
                  <hi>Adam</hi> by his pride was conquered in Paradiſe. Alſo Romes peace and ſecuritie after the Carthaginian wars were ended, did her more hurt than all the former battailes.</p>
               <p>And Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith of the Church:<note n="e" place="margin">Ber. Ser. <hi>33.</hi> in Cant.</note> 
                  <hi>Amara fuit prius in nece Martyrum, amarior poſtea in conflictu haereticorum, amariſsima vero nunc in moribus domeſtico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum:</hi> intimating that ſhe was more hurt by the licentious
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:21343:35"/> liues of her children in the dayes of her peace, than by the bloud of her Martyrs, or her conflict with haeretikes.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Applicat. </seg>
                  </label> And may it not be truely ſaid of this Church and land, that the raine of proſperitie, peace, and plenty (falling not by drops, but by full ſhowers vpon it, in the late, long, and happy reigne of our euer to be remembred, and thrice re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned <hi>Deborah,</hi> and our now peacefull <hi>Salomon</hi>) hath done more hurt to this building, by rotting many beames, and rafters thereof, than thoſe tempeſtuous whirle-winds, and violent torrents of perſecution in Queene <hi>Maries</hi> dayes? for whereas there were then glorious confeſsions of the truth in the midſt of the fire, now there be dayly A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtacies from it in the dayes of peace. And our moralitie is ſo corrupted with our long peace and proſperitie, that there was neuer more lying and diſſembling in Creta, ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and forſwearing in Carthage gormandizing in Capua, or <hi>Semiplacentia,</hi> drunkenneſſe in Germany, pride in Spaine, or wantonneſſe in Italy, than is at this day in our land: as if the vices of all nations did meete here as in their Center, or as if our land were the ſinke or common ſewer for the ſinnes of all nations to runne into.</p>
               <p>Shall we thus repay the Lord for his bleſsings? ſhall we now begin to<note n="f" place="margin">Num: 11.5, 6.</note> loath our <hi>Manna</hi> that hath thus long fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len dayly about our tents, and hanker againe after the fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pots of the Romiſh Aegypt? ſhall we ſurfet of our <hi>quailes?</hi> and being full fed with Gods bleſsings,<note n="g" place="margin">Deut. 8.10.</note> ſpurne with the heele againſt him, and turne our backes vpon his mercy-ſeat? God forbid.</p>
               <p>Let vs not thus turne Gods grace into wantonneſſe, and repay him with our foule and crying ſins in ſtead of thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullneſſe for his bleſsings: (like the ſea that receiues ſweet waters from the fountaines of the earth, and returnes them ſalt and bitter:) leaſt we incurre the curſe of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate Iewes.<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 69.22, 23 Rom. 11.9, 10.</note> 
                  <hi>Let their table be made a ſnare, and a trap, and a ſtumbling blocke, &amp;c. and the things that ſhould haue beene for their weale be vnto them an ocaſion of falling.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>2.</hi> Tent. perſuaſ.</note>2. With this tentation of proſperitie, I may conioyne the Churches ſecond tentation, by the pleaſing ſouth-winds
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:21343:35"/> of haereticall perſuaſions: becauſe they are moſt rife in the dayes of the Churches peace. With theſe winds hath the houſe of the liuing God beene forcibly beat vpon, and the ſhip of his true Church beene violently toſſed, almoſt in all ages in the troubleſome ſea of this world: for haeretikes and ſchiſmatikes, (being themſelues carryed away with theſe<note n="b" place="margin">Iren. li <hi>3.</hi> c <hi>13.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>three diſaſtrous whirle-winds.</hi> 1. With the vncleane ſpirit of error: 2. With their owne frenzie whereof they labour: 3. <hi>Magis ſtudio contradicendi,</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Cypr ad De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met. ſect. prima</note> 
                  <hi>quam voto diſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di: .i.</hi> Rather with an itching humour of ſingularity to contradict the truth, than a true zealous humility to learne it, ſeeke to driue others with them into error, and ſo they willfully<note n="d" place="margin">Mat. 15.14.</note> blind, leade the woefully blinded with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues into the ditch of deſtruction. But he who is driuen of theſe winds,<note n="e" place="margin">Aug. Ti. <hi>1.</hi> in Ioh. Mat. <hi>25.30.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Non portum ſed planctum inueniet,</hi> ſhall in the end arriue at no other harbour, but where ſhall be wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping and gnaſhing of teeth.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Applicat. </seg>
                  </label> And from theſe diſaſtrous winds our Church is not free now in the dayes of her peace: for there ſwarmes among vs corner-creeping Prieſts, and Ieſuites, who (like ſubtle foxes) ſeeke to vndermine, and roote vp the flouriſhing vine of this Church and State; by<note n="f" place="margin">2. Tim. 3.6.</note> 
                  <hi>creeping into hovſes, and lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding captiue ſilly women laden with diuers luſts,</hi> and ſilly Ide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ots apt to beleeue whatſoeuer they tell them without fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tryal of their doctrine by the touchſtone of truth. This kind of fiſhing they learned from Sathan himfelfe: who firſt<note n="g" place="margin">Gen. 3.1.</note> attempted the woman, that by her hee might tempt the man: vſing the wife as a trappe to catch her husband. And from the auncient Gnoſtikes: of whoſe ring-leader <hi>Marcus Jrenaeus</hi> reports:<note n="h" place="margin">Iren. li. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Maximè circa mulieres occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patus eſt.</hi> His principall aime and chiefeſt buſineſſe was to ſeduce ſilly women.</p>
               <p>And as the diuell at firſt,<note n="a" place="margin">Cypr. de vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate Eccl. ſect. <hi>5</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Verbis mendacibus blandiens rudes animas incauta credulitate decepit;</hi> deceiued the poore innocent ſoules of our firſt parents by his lying &amp; flattering words, praeſuming vpon their heedleſſe credulitie: ſo they by their lying and flattering words, (which are<note n="b" place="margin">Lact Jnſtit. li. <hi>5.</hi> c <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Mella ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenum tegentia,</hi> pills of poyſon lapt in hony:) creepe into
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:21343:36"/> the ſoules of their ouer-credulous Diſciples, and blinding them with the falſe vizar of the name of the ancient Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church, lead them hoodwinked to their owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uiticaal traps to catch poore ſoules.</note>For firſt, they tell them (and that onely truely:)<note n="c" place="margin">Cypr. de vnit. Eccleſ.</note> 
                  <hi>That out of the true Church there is no ſaluation:</hi> but all that are out of it muſt needs periſh, as all that were out of the arke, were drowned in the deluge.</p>
               <p>Secondly, they falſly aſſume that the Church of Rome (as now it is) is the onely true, auncient, Catholike Church: and the Proteſtants are haeretikes, and their Church ſprung vp but lately ſince <hi>Luthers</hi> dayes.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, they teach their diſciples, that the Scriptures are obſcure, and dangerous for lay-men, and ſilly women to meddle withall, (becauſe the reading and miſunderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Scriptures hath bred many haereſies:) and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is enough for them to relye vpon the definitions of their mother, the Romiſh Church, and directions of their ghoſtly Fathers, without any further ſearch or inquiry: thus thieues put out the candle that ſhould diſcouer them.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, they tell them that it is haereſie for a lay-man to diſpute in points of faith, neither muſt they reade any bookes written againſt the Romiſh Religion, or any part thereof: nor conferre with any Proteſtant miniſter, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther able to defend his religion, but in all doubts repaire to their ghoſtly fathers for reſolution.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, they extoll deuout ignorance and implicite faith to the skies: and tell them, that ſuch ignorantly deuout ſoules ſhall haue the benefit of other mens knowledge. So they canonize the Colliars faith, and make it their ſeduced diſciples Creed to beleeue as the Church beleeues. Now when ſilly ignorant ſoules haue deepely drunke in theſe principles, what maruaile is it, if they bee eaſily peruer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and hardly conuerted, when their ſeducing teachers haue thus hedged in their eyes, eares, and hearts, that they ſhould not heare, nor vnderſtand?</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Hortatio.</note>Wherefore ſeeing theſe<note n="a" place="margin">Mat 7.15.</note> 
                  <hi>Wolues in ſheepes cloathing,</hi> (who like the wolues of <hi>Africa</hi> faine the voice of ſheepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:21343:36"/> to deuoure the flocke) be ſo buſie to infect our flocks with Popery, let vs be as vigilant to continue them in the truth: Now (if euer) S. <hi>Bern.</hi> exhortation is to be put in practiſe:<note n="b" place="margin">Ber. li. <hi>3</hi> de conſid c. <hi>10</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Danda eſt opera vt increduli conuertantur, conuerſi non auertantur, auerſi reuertantur, &amp;c. We that are Miniſters of the word, muſt ſedulouſly endeauour that thoſe which do not rightly beleeue, may be conuerted, and thoſe that are turned out of the way, may returne into the right way againe, and thoſe that are conuerted, may not be turned away, and thoſe that are peruerſe may be directed into the paths of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and thoſe that are ſubuerted may bee recalled into the wayes of truth, and that the ſubuerters themſelues ſhould haue their errors conuinced by the euidence of truth, that either themſelues may be reclaimed, or they may looſe all power and authority to ſubuert others.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>1</hi> Ad epiſt.</note>Let me therefore beſeech you (Reuerend Fathers) in the bowells of Chriſt Ieſus (who am vnworthy to counſaile you) that as yee are <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Biſhops, or ouerſeers in name,<note n="c" place="margin">Act. 20.28.</note> ſo ye would indeed (in theſe dangerous dayes) with a moſt vigilant eye ouerſee the flocke of Chriſt committed to your ſeuerall charges, which Chriſt hath purchaſed with his owne blood. Ye ſit at the ſterne of this ſhip of the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Church, and are skilfull in your compaſſe, O let not theſe diſaſtrous winds carry it the contrary way, but guide it ſtill (as ye haue done) in the way of truth to the hauen of hapines. Ye are the<note n="d" place="margin">Mar. 13.34.</note> porters of this houſe &amp; fold of Chriſt, and haue the keyes of iuriſdiction in your hands to let in and out: O watch therefore that theſe<note n="e" place="margin">Ioh. 10.2.</note> thieues and rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers breake not in, and ſteale away the ſheepe of Chriſt from his fold, whoſe ſoules are moſt<note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 116.15.</note> deare and pretious in his ſight. And ſee that euery <hi>Archippus</hi> vnder you in your ſeuerall Diocaeſes, doe both by preaching and catechizing (according to his Maieſties late pious, and moſt Chriſtian directions)<note n="g" place="margin">Col. 4.17.</note> take heed to the miniſtery that he hath recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in the Lord, that he fulfill it.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>2.</hi> Ad Mag.</note>And let all religious Magiſtrates in their places ſeeke with godly<note n="a" place="margin">2 <hi>Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 35.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Joſiah</hi> to purge Gods houſe where it is pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted either with error or ſinne: and (with zealous)<note n="b" place="margin">Neh. 4.1, 9.</note> 
                  <hi>Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah,</hi>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:21343:37"/> endeauour to reaedifie the ruine of Gods Ieruſalem, and to defend this building againſt all malicious <hi>Tobiahs,</hi> and <hi>Sanballats</hi> that ſeeke to hinder it.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>3</hi> Ad priuatos.</note>And let all priuate men take heed, that theſe wily Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents creepe not into their boſomes by their ſubtle inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations: but let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hold faſt the truth that they haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in the Lord, and if any (though an<note n="c" place="margin">Gal. 1.16.</note> angell from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen) bring them any other doctrine, let them hold him accurſed.<note n="d" place="margin">Cypr. de vnit. Eccl. ſect. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Nutet enim neceſſe eſt &amp; vagetur, &amp; ſpiritu er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roris arreptus (velut puluis) ventiletur qui ſalutaris viae non tenet veritatem:</hi> for he muſt needs totter, and wander, and (being driuen with the ſpirit of error) be carryed away as<note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. 1.4.</note> duſt or chaffe, which the wind ſcatters away from the face of the earth, that doth not keepe the truth of that way that leades to ſaluation.<note n="f" place="margin">Eph. 4.14.</note> Be not therefore (like children) wauering, and carryed away with euery wind of vaine do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, but follow the truth in loue, and in all things growe vp to him that is the head, namely, Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>:</hi> Tent. perſecut.</note>3. The third ſort of temptations wherewith the Church is aſſaulted, is affliction and perſecution: compared to the bluſtering Northwinds, and violent flouds which beat vpon this houſe: for the true Church is like<note n="g" place="margin">Gen. 7.18. &amp; 8.4</note> 
                  <hi>Noahs</hi> arke: ſtill floating on the waters of trouble, till ſhee come to reſt on Ararat the Mount of God: for<note n="h" place="margin">Act. 14.22.</note> through many tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons we muſt enter into Gods kingdome.<note n="i" place="margin">2 Tim, 3.12.</note> And all that will liue godly in Chriſt Ieſus muſt ſuffer perſecution: for<note n="k" place="margin">Aug in Pſ. <hi>31.</hi>
                  </note> though God had one ſonne without ſinne, yet he hath none without affliction. A Chriſtians life is like a nauigation in a tempeſtuous ſea: the harbor whence we launch is our mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wombe, the port whereto we are bound is the hauen of heauen, but the interim betweene, (the whole time of our ſayling in the troubleſome ſea of this world) is full of tempeſts, full of Pyrats. So that Reuerend <hi>Luther</hi> ſaid true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: <hi>Qui non eſt crucianus, non eſt Chriſtianus:</hi> no croſſe, no Chriſtian: conſonant to that of the Apoſtle:<note n="l" place="margin">Heb. 12.5.</note> If ye bee without chaſtiſement, whereof all are partakers, then are ye baſtards, and not ſonnes.</p>
               <p>And concerning the Churches perſecutions, that of <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:21343:37"/> concerning Troy, may moſt truely bee ſpoken of the true Church Militant,<note n="a" place="margin">Homer Iliad.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. She hath but a little breathing time from her continuall warfare: for theſe two contrary armies (<hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Amalech</hi>) are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes fighting.<note n="b" place="margin">Ex 17. vlt.</note> God will haue warre with myſticall <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malech, (.i.</hi> the Church malignant) from generation to ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration.<note n="c" place="margin">Ser. <hi>92.</hi> de Temp.</note> As ſoone as the Iſraelites had dranke of the rocke, forthwith they warred againſt <hi>Amalech:</hi> to teach vs that we no ſooner drinke of the rocke Chriſt, and are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporated into him, but forthwith we muſt prepare our ſelues for a warfare.</p>
               <p>For the viſible Church is like<note n="d" place="margin">Gen. 25.22.</note> 
                  <hi>Rebeccaes</hi> wombe: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in are bred ſonnes of contrary natures (as <hi>Iacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau</hi>) and theſe ſtriue together in her wombe from her very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of thee.<note n="e" place="margin">Apoc. 12.5.15</note> As ſoone as euer the woman is deliuered of a manchild, (that is, the Church hath brought foorth a ſonne to God:) preſently the dragon doth caſt out flouds of water out of his mouth to deſtroy it.</p>
               <p>This auncient enmity betweene the old ſerpent and the ſeed of the woman began in Paradiſe:<note n="f" place="margin">Gen. 3.15<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>I will put enmity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene thy ſeed and her ſeed, &amp;c.</hi> And forthwith it began to breake out by open perſecution: for the perſecution of the Church of the old Teſtament began with<note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 48.</note> 
                  <hi>Abels</hi> murther:<note n="h" place="margin">Aug. de Ciu. dei. li. <hi>18.</hi> c. <hi>51.</hi>
                  </note> (<hi>Dedicat Eccleſiam ſanguine:</hi> He dedicates the Church to God by his bloud): and of the Church of the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with cruell<note n="i" place="margin">Mat. 2.16.</note> 
                  <hi>Herods</hi> bloudy butchering the poore In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants of Bethleem: who were Martyrs, <hi>Opere, et ſi non vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntate</hi> in the worke it ſelfe, or their outward act of ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, though not in will or intention: whence S. <hi>Aug.</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them,<note n="k" place="margin">Aug. de ſanct. ſect. <hi>11.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Primitias Martyrum:</hi> The firſt fruites of the Martyrs of Chriſt: for they ſuffered for Chriſt, though they knew not for whom they ſuffered. <hi>Pro Chriſto occiduntur paruuli pro iuſtitia moritur innocentia.</hi> The little Infants of Bethleem dyed for Chriſt: innocence dyed for righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: for ſo Chriſt is called,<note n="i" place="margin">Ier. 23.6.</note> 
                  <hi>The Lord our righteouſneſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And euer ſince<note n="k" place="margin">Gen. 21.9, 10</note> 
                  <hi>Iſhmael</hi> hath perſecuted <hi>Iſaac:</hi> that is, thoſe who are borne after the fleſh, them that are borne af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſpirit. In the ten primitiue perſecutions, the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:21343:38"/> of the Churches field were watered with ſtreames of bloud, and this made it the more fertile: for l the bloud of the Martyrs is the ſeed of the Church.<note place="margin">Cypr. de dupli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci. Mart.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And euer ſince that <hi>bloudy Whore of Babylon</hi> hath borne ſway in the world, ſhe hath made her ſelfe<note n="a" place="margin">Apoc. 19.6.</note> drunke with the blood of the Saints, and Martyrs of Ieſus: by her bloudy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition, cruell maſſacres, horrid treaſons, and open perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions: for where ſhe may preuaile, ſhe vſeth no other ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments to maintaine her religion, but whipes, racks, gib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bets, ſtrappadoes, fire, and fagot: (as<note n="b" place="margin">See <hi>Foxe</hi> his Acts and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents of he Church.</note> here in England in Queene <hi>Maries</hi> dayes,) for ſhe ſeekes not to perſuade, but to compell: and delights to tyrannize ouer mens conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Their very mercies are cruell: there is more mercy to be found of the mercileſſe elements (to wit, the flaming fire, and raging ſea) than at their hands where they may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile, and therefore from their bloudy hands and cruell teeth the Lord deliuer vs.</p>
               <p>For we may ſafely pray, <hi>Vt</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Cypr. de mort.</note> 
                  <hi>Martyriu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deſit anim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> that we his ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts being hurt by no perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, may alwaies glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie his holy name in his holy church (as our church praies in our Letanie: becauſe God requires not our bloud, but our faith (as that bleſſed Martyr S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſaith:) but if the ſtormie winds and violent flouds of perſecution for the truth ſhould beate vpon the houſe of this Church, we muſt alſo pray and that earneſtly, <hi>Ne animus deſit Marty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>:</hi> that our minds be not wanting vnto Martirdome: but that we may be willing to ſhed our bloud for him and his truth, that ſhed his precious bloud for vs &amp; our ſaluation: for theſe be the winds and ſtormes, that make a true &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect triall indeed who haue built the ſpirituall houſes of their ſoules on a ſure, and who on a ſandy foundation: and which building will ſtand,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1</hi> Perfeuerautia a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ctorum.</note> and which fall to ruine.</p>
               <p>Firſt, thoſe that haue built the ſpirituall houſes of their ſoules vpon the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ocke Chriſt, and his ſacred truth, not by hearing or knowing onely, but by beleeuing and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſing, will outſtand all theſe tryalls of raine, flouds, and ſtormie winds, and<note n="d" place="margin">Pſal. 125.1.</note> ſtand faſt like Mount Sion, which cannot be remooued, but ſtandeth faſt for euer: for of ſuch
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:21343:38"/> a building it is here ſaid, though all theſe beat vpon it, <hi>Jt fell not, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> writing vpon this place, ſaith,<note n="e" place="margin">Chryſ. in Loc.</note> 
                  <hi>Boni firmitatem Petrae conſtantiae virtute ſuperant, &amp;c.</hi> The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy of good and faithfull men exceedes the firmenes of a rocke.<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> A rock though neuer ſo much beaten againſt by the waues and winds, ſtands immooueable, and not hurt, as ſcorning their violence: ſo a faithfull Chriſtian (becauſe the Lord is his rocke, and he is built vpon the rocke Chriſt Ieſus) ſcornes the force and malice of the diuell, and all his confaederates: knowing that though Sathan raiſe vp a mighty wind to ſhake him on euery ſide,)<note n="a" place="margin">Iob 1.10.</note> as the wind did the foure corners of <hi>Jobs</hi> houſe), yet hee cannot ſhake him off his foundation though he vexe him with all his ſtormes, yet none of theſe, nor the very gates of hell can preuaile a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, becauſe he is built vpon a rocke.</p>
               <p>Such a one was<note n="b" place="margin">Gen. 37, 39. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Joſeph:</hi> who ſerued God not onely in <hi>Potiphars</hi> houſe, and <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Court, but in the priſon al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his feet were faſt in the ſtockes, &amp; their ó entred into his ſoule. And<note n="c" place="margin">Iob 19.25.</note> 
                  <hi>Job</hi> who (when God ſet him vp as a marke to ſhoot at) ſtill held faſt his confidence in his redeemer: <hi>J know that my redeemer liueth, &amp;c.</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Dan. 3.16, 17.</note> And the three chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deren, whom neither the threats of <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> nor his angry countenance, nor the ſight of the fierie furnace, could deterre from worſhipping their God, nor cauſe them to fall downe before the golden Image. And<note n="e" place="margin">Dan. 6.12, 13.</note> 
                  <hi>Daniel:</hi> whom nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the fauours of <hi>Darius</hi> could allure, nor his irrecouera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble edict compell to deſiſt from praying to his God, but he choſe rather to be caſt into the den of Lyons. I could be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt infinit in inſtances of the like kind out of the Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall hiſtories: where we find S. <hi>And.</hi> kiſsing his croſſe, &amp; imbracing it with a <hi>Salue Sancte crux, &amp;c. Ignat.</hi> inuiting the wild beaſts to deuoure him: ſaying, <hi>I am the Lords wheat &amp; muſt be ground with the teeth of wild beaſts:</hi> &amp; S. <hi>Laurence</hi> vpon his fierie gridiro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (which was to him as a bed of down) outbrauing the tyrant <hi>Decius,</hi> and telling him that one ſide was waſted enough, he ſhould now turne vp the other.</p>
               <p>But I ſhall need no more inſtances, ſeeing Saint <hi>Paul.</hi>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:21343:39"/> in the name of all Gods Saints, bids open defiance to Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than and his complices,<note n="f" place="margin">Rom. 8.35. &amp;c</note> Who ſhall ſeparate vs from the loue of Chriſt? Shall tribulation, diſtreſſe, or perſecution, or famine, or nakedneſſe, or perill, or ſwords: no, in all theſe we are more than conquerours through him that loued vs.</p>
               <p>Not that Gods Saints and Martyrs are <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, altogether ſenceleſſe (like ſtoicks or ſtocks rather:) for they feele the ſmart and paine of their tortures, els they could not be va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant Martyrs: (ſeeing true fortitude conſiſtes in the patient bearing of thoſe things which are moſt afflictiue to fleſh and bloud:) but they are comforted: 1. In the ſenſe of Gods preſent mercies:<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 94.19.</note> whoſe comforts doe refreſh their ſoules: 2. In the certaine expectation of their future glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry:<note n="b" place="margin">2 Cor. 4.17.</note> 
                  <hi>for we know that theſe light afflictions which are but for a moment, doe cauſe vnto vs a farre more excellent and ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall weight of glory:</hi> So that in all their afflictions &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions, faith ſupports them that they fall not: hope com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts them that they deſpaire not: patience quiets them that they murmure not, and their inward peace of conſcience, ſweetens their outward troubles with comfortable cordials that they faint not.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Chryſ. in Loc.</note>As he therefore that beates vpon an Adamant, is him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe beaten with his owne blowes (for he is wearied, but the Adamant not pierced, which is impenetrable:) And the waues that daſh againſt a rocke are themſelues broken, but the rocke ſtandeth immooueable: and hee that<note n="d" place="margin">Act. 9.5.</note> kickes as gainſt the pricks is himſelf wounded with his own ſtroaks: ſo he that perſecutes Gods faithfull children, hurts him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe not them: for he makes them haue fellowſhip with Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, in being partakers of his ſufferings, and bearing in their bodies <hi>ſtigmata Chriſti:</hi> that is, the prints of his precious wounds: while himſelfe hath fellowſhip with <hi>Iudas</hi> in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traying and perſecuting Chriſt in his members.<note n="e" place="margin">Phil. 1.8.</note> 
                  <hi>Be nothing therefore terrified with your aduerſaries: which to them is a token of perdition, but to you of ſaluation, and that of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ratio.</note>The reaſon of this immooueable conſtancy and ſtability of Gods Saints is,<note n="f" place="margin">V. 25.</note> Becauſe the ſpirituall aedifice of their ſoules and bodies is built vpon a rocke: for they haue theſe
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:21343:39"/> three rocks to ſupport and ſtrengthen them in all their rrou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles: 1. The might and mercy of God the Father: who is the maine pillar of power, and fountaine of goodneſſe: of whoſe fauour they doubt not, becauſe he hath paſſed it vnto them in his holy word by promiſe, indenture, couenant, and<note n="g" place="margin">Heb. 6.13. &amp;c.</note> oath: and that before immooueable<note n="h" place="margin">1 Ioh. 5.7, 8,</note> witneſſes, the beſt in heauen, and the beſt on earth. 2. The merits of Chriſt: for their true and ſauing faith doth reſt it ſelfe in the preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous wounds of Chriſt, (as the<note n="k" place="margin">Cant. 2.14.</note> doues in the clefts of the rocks,) that it cannot bee remooued. 3. The comforts of the holy Ghoſt: who dwells in them as in his<note n="l" place="margin">1 Cor. 6.19.</note> temples, and reignes in their hearts as in his kingdome: directing them into all truth and goodneſſe, and comforting them in all their troubles: as being the<note n="a" place="margin">Eph. 1.13, 14.</note> ſeale of their adoption, and earneſt of their aeternall inheritance. And with theſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pregnable bulwarks, the fortreſſe of their faith is ſo ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened, that neither raine, flouds, nor wind,<note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 8.38, 39</note> height, nor depth, life, nor death, principalities, nor powers, &amp;c. nor the gates of hell, nor the whole force and power of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of darkneſſe can once ſhake, much leſſe ouerthrow it, <hi>becauſe it is builded vpon a rocke.</hi> For though Gods Saints bee troubled on euery ſide, yet are they not diſtreſſed,<note n="c" place="margin">2 Cor. 4.8, 9.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>.i. Haeſitantes non haerentes, (Arr. Mont.)</hi> perplexed, but not in deſpaire: perſecuted, but not forſaken, caſt downe, but not caſt away, or deſtroied.</p>
               <p>But if any build vpon the ſand of <hi>humane Traditions,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>1</hi> Caſus malorum</note> or their owne fancies, or the worlds vanities, both building and builders fall together (like<note n="d" place="margin">Dan. 2.35.</note> 
                  <hi>Nebuchadnezzars</hi> Image, when the ſtone hewen out of the mountaine without hands fell vpon it:) and become like the chaffe of the ſummer threſhing floures, or the ſand they build vpon, or the duſt which the wind ſcatters from the face of the earth.<note place="margin">Iuſt. prim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. He that goes to build vp the ruines of <hi>Babell</hi> in his ſoule, ſhall with it fall to ruine: for as one Angell cryed concerning <hi>Babilon,</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Apoc. 14 8, 9, 10</note> 
                  <hi>Cecidit cecidit,</hi> It is fallen, it is fallen: ſo another angell immediately following the former, cryed wieh a loud voice: <hi>If any man worſhip the beaſt, and receiue his marke in his forehead, or his hand, the ſame ſhall drinke of
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:21343:40"/> the wine of the wrath of God powred out without mixture in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the cup of his indignation, and ſhall be tormented with fire and brimſtone for euer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Maruaile not therefore at the Apoſtacy of many to Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery in theſe dayes: they are ſuch as neuer built on the rock of truth and right: but on the ſands of their owne fancies, or the world, (by preſumption, ſecuritie, worldlineſſe, or hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie) and therefore God ſuffers them to fall into er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, as a iuſt puniſhment of their ſinnes: and they ſhall at length fall into the fierie lake, as an aeternall puniſhment, both of their ſinnes, and errors.<note n="f" place="margin">2 Theſ. 2.10.21, 12.</note> Becauſe they receiued not the loue of the truth that they might be ſaued, for this cauſe God ſhal ſend them a ſtrong deluſion that they ſhould beleeue a lye, that they might be damned, who beleeued not the truth, but had pleaſure in vnrighteouſnes.</p>
               <p>For<note n="a" place="margin">Cypr. imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectum in Loc.</note> how ſhould he abide in Chriſt that neuer was in Chriſt? or how ſhould the truth hold him that neuer held the truth? or righteouſneſſe preſerue him that neuer kept the wayes of righteouſnes? No, no, ſuch buildings (though they be built as high as the tower of <hi>Babell,</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Gen. 11.4.</note> whoſe top did euen reach to heauen, or as the tombe of <hi>Manſeolus,</hi> or <hi>Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramides of Aegypt:</hi> and be as faire, and ſtately for outward ſhew as the temple of<note n="c" place="margin">Act 19.27.</note> 
                  <hi>Diana</hi> at <hi>Epheſus</hi> (the wonderment of the world:) or the coſtly palace of <hi>Alcinoous,</hi> (the walls whereof were braſſe, the gates gold, and the entries ſiluer): yet downe they muſt, they and their builders ſhall fall: and<note n="d" place="margin">Iinex. <hi>v. 27</hi> Ruina magna.</note> 
                  <hi>their fall ſhall be great.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The fall of an houſe is great: firſt, when it falls not in part but totaly: (that is, not the roofe, or a wal, or a roome onely), but is turned topſey-turuey from the very fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: 2. when it falls finally and irrecouerably neuer to be rayſed vp againe like the walls of Iericho.<note n="e" place="margin">Ioſ. 6.26.</note> Such I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded ſhall in Gods due time bee the fall of <hi>Babilon</hi> (as a<note n="f" place="margin">M. <hi>Higgo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s</hi> in his myſticall Babilon.</note> learned Diuine of ours hath of late euidently prooued) though the Babiloniſh architects labour with all their arr. and induſtry to repaire the ruines of Babell: but<note n="g" place="margin">Pſal. 127.1.</note> 
                  <hi>except the Lord build the houſe, their labour is but loſt that build it,</hi> and the Lord hath decreed and denounced the fall thereof
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:21343:40"/> by that<note n="h" place="margin">Apoc. 14.12.</note> euerlaſting Goſpell, which the Angell brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world: therefore downe it muſt, and the fall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſhall be great, and ſhall cruſh all that wittingly, willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and wilfully fall with it, and vnder it, (as the<note n="i" place="margin">Oct. 26, 1623.</note> late fall of an houſe did ſome adhaerents vnto Babilon) and preſſe them downe (if they ſpeedily repent not) to the bottome of hell.</p>
               <p>And ſuch alſo will be the fall of all worldlings,<note place="margin">Iuſt ſecunda,</note> &amp; other fooliſh builders on the ſand, if they ſpeedily conuert not, and become wiſe builders, to builde on the rocke Chriſt and his Sacred truth, both by beleeuing and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing. As here their fall was great, when they wittingly, and willingly conſented vnto ſinne; and greater, when they acted it, and greateſt of all, when they perſiſted in it: ſo hereafter their fall ſhall be exceeding great: Not like<note n="k" place="margin">Gen. 3 23.</note> 
                  <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dams</hi> onely, from a paradiſe of pleaſure to a wilderneſſe of wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>: (for ſo they fall here when they fall from truth to er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, and from righteouſnes to ſinne and wickednes: but like <hi>Lucifers,</hi> who fell like<note n="l" place="margin">Luc. 10.11.</note> lightning, (that is, ſwiftly and ſuddainely from the height of heauen to the depth of hell: and from being an <hi>Angell of light,</hi> and a pure ſtarre of coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall brightneſſe to be an <hi>angell of aeternall night,</hi> and the blacke Prince of infernall darknes.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Applicat. </seg>
                  </label> To the end therefore that wee may eſcape this fearefull fall and irrecouerable Mine of haeretiks, prophane wretches, worldlings, and hypocrites, let vs build on the firme rocke of Chriſt and his heauenly truth, both by hearing and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſing.</p>
               <p>Wee of this land are bound to God for innumerable bleſsings: namely, <hi>a Religious King, a hopefull Prince, a fruitfull land</hi> (like <hi>Canaan</hi> flowing with milke and hony, or <hi>Eden</hi> the garden of the Lord:) alſo <hi>goodly and populous ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and townes,</hi> and <hi>flouriſhing Vniuerſities,</hi> and <hi>Innes of Court,</hi> (which like <hi>Theopbraſtus</hi> Perſian tree) doe at the ſame time bud, bloſſome, and bring forth fruit. So that we may ſay of <hi>England</hi> (as one did of <hi>Rhodes,) Semper in Sole ſita eſt:</hi> for we haue had a long ſunne-ſhine of proſperitie, peace, and plenty: and withall the ſunne-ſhine of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell:
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:21343:41"/> which (as <hi>Luther</hi> ſaid) is <hi>Genus generaliſsimum om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium bonorum,</hi> the well head of our happineſſe: for hereby we may build on the rocke, while other our neighbour na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions build on the ſand.</p>
               <p>Seeing therefore God hath truſted vs with ſuch a trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, let vs be thankefull for it: and ſhew our thankfullnes: firſt, <hi>in imbracing this Goſpell of peace peaceably,</hi> as the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects of the Prince of peace. Let vs not ſtand ſtriuing (as too many haue vainely done already too long) about the ſwadling cloutes of holy Religion (namely Clericall ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bites, and other comely Ceremonies) leaſt while we ſtriue about theſe ouermuch, wee endanger the body or ſubſtance of true Religion, let vs not any longer r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd in ſunder the<note n="a" place="margin">Cypr. de vnit. Eccleſ.</note> ſeameleſſe coat of Chriſt (the vnitie of the Church) by our needleſſe con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> about th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>gs. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ee<note n="b" place="margin">Gal. 5.15.</note> 
                  <hi>bite and deuoure one another, let vs take heed leaſt we bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed one of another:</hi> and while we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>be th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Churches peace, we depriue her of her proſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ie, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> make an open wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> (as this brea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h hath already done too much:) for thoſe proud and cruell Babylonians to ruine our Ieruſal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m: who ſay of it in their hearts:<note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 127.7.</note> 
                  <hi>Downe with it, downe with it euen to the ground.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll Miniſters or members of one Church, (which is<note n="d" place="margin">Cypr. ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>Vna Colu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ba,</hi> one<note n="e" place="margin">Cant. 5.2.</note> do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of Chriſt: let vs haue all the douelike ſpirit of humi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>itie, charit, peace, &amp; vnitie: for the doues of one houſe liue together, loue together, fly to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, flocke together kiſſe each other, and in all reſpects performe the l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wes of loue, peace, and vnanimity. So let vs liue and loue together, and (with the firſt bel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>euers of the Primitiue Church) be all of<note n="a" place="margin">Act. 4.32.</note> 
                  <hi>one heart and one ſoule.</hi> Let all miniſters preach, and people pray for the peace of our Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem:<note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. 122.6, 7.</note> 
                  <hi>for if peace be within her walls, plenteouſneſſe will be within her palaces.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Let vs that are built on this rocke of truth, bring forth the fruits of holines and true righteouſnes. So S. <hi>Ier.</hi> ſaid of the Chriſtians of his dayes:<note n="c" place="margin">Hieron. Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m. Comment. in Ezech.</note> 
                  <hi>Scripturarum cupimus verba in opera vertere, &amp; non dicere ſancta ſed facere:</hi> we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to turne the words of the Scripture into workes, and
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:21343:41"/> not to ſpeake of, but to doe the workes of holineſſe.</p>
               <p>As the naturall life lies hid in the heart (the fountaine of the vitall ſpirits) and yet Phyſitions iudge of it by the pulſe in the arme: ſo the ſpirituall life of a Chriſtian (to wit his regeneration) lies hid in the heart and ſoule, and yet men iudge of it by the motion of the arme (the exerciſe of good workes) <hi>for</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Mat 7.10.</note> 
                  <hi>the tree is knowne by his fruites.</hi> We cannot iudge of the life of grace, and power of true Religion in the ſoules of men: 1. By the eyes: for many lift vp their eyes to heauen (by ſeeming ſhewes of ſanctitie) when their hearts lye grouel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng on the earth, yea mudling in the earth by baſe worldlineſſe, and groſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> carnalitie. 2. Nor by the eares: fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> there be many<note n="e" place="margin">Iam. 1.22.</note> 
                  <hi>hearers of the word, but not do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the ſame, deceiuing their owne ſoules:</hi> 3. Nor by the tongu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>: fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> many<note n="f" place="margin">Mat. 15.8. &amp; 7.21.</note> 
                  <hi>draw neere to God with their mouths, and honour him with their lips, when their hearts are far from him,</hi> and cry with a zealous ingemination, <hi>Lord, Lord, and yet doe not the will of their heauenly Father.</hi> But by the arme or hand: that is, by doing cheerefully, ſincerely, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly the things that God commandeth.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">Cant. 5.1. &amp; 6.2.</note>Chriſt the bridegroome comes into his garden, not to refreſh himſelfe vnder the ſhadow of the trees, or to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the greene lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es, or to crop the buds, and bloſſomes, but to gather the fruits, that his friends may eate abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly: for then Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſt feedes when his friends feed, the head is nouriſhe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in his members.<note n="h" place="margin">Mat. 25.40.</note> 
                  <hi>In as much as yee haue done it vnto me of theſe little ones ye haue done it vnto me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let therefore the word of God<note n="i" place="margin">Col. 3.16.</note> dwell in you (as it dwels among you) plenteouſly that ye may bee<note n="k" place="margin">1 Tim. 6.18.</note> rich in good workes, ready to diſtribute, willing to communicate to the poore and needy<note n="l" place="margin">Eſa. 58 7, 8.</note> dealing your bread to the hungry, &amp; drinke to the thirſty, bringing the poore that are caſt out into your houſes, couering the naked with a garment, &amp; not hiding your ſelues from your owne fleſh: then ſhall your light breake forth as the morning, and your health ſpring foorth ſpeedily, your righteouſnes ſhall goe before you, and the glory of the Lord ſhall be your reward. And then ſhall God<note n="a" place="margin">Apoc. 20.1.</note> chaine vp Sathan in the bottomleſſe pit, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:21343:42"/> the force and malice, of wicked men that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not hurt vs,<note n="b" place="margin">Aug in Exod.</note> 
                  <hi>Malorum poteſtas deficit in muſcis,</hi> The po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of the Magitians failes in the flies: for Sathan cannot doe the leaſt thing without Gods permiſsion. If therefore we<note n="c" place="margin">Eccleſ. 12. <hi>vlt.</hi>
                  </note> feare the Lord and keepe his commandements, heare his word and doe it, euen thoſe ſtormes, flouds and winds, which Sathan ſtirres vp to caſt downe our ſpiriruall buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, ſhall blow our happines, and land the ſhips of our ſoules and bodies at laſt in the hauen of heauen.</p>
               <p>Now let euery heart ſtretch forth an hand, &amp; apply what hath beene ſpoken to himſelfe, and pray earneſtly for the aſsiſtance of Gods Spirit that he may ſo doe: for we may preach, and you heare, and both looſe our labour, except there be a drawing of the father, a touch of the Sonne, and an inſpiration of the Holy-Ghoſt; but if theſe concurre, then God himſelfe makes the Sermon, and builds vp there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the ſpirituall Edifices of our Soules, &amp; makes them ſtand faſt for euer: and ſo the fruit of a few houres hearing ſhall be eternity of dayes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer.</head>
               <p>Grant vs grace therefore (O Lord) to bee doers of thy word, not hearers only, deceiuing our own ſouls: &amp; vouchſafe ſo to aſsiſt vs with thy holy Spirit in this our building, that we may not build the ſpirituall Edifices of our ſoules, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on <hi>humane traditions,</hi> (with ſuperſtitious Papiſts;) or vpon our <hi>vaine preſumption</hi> of thy mercy, (with prophane &amp; ſecure ſinners) or vpon <hi>the periſhing vanities of this world</hi> (with fooliſh Mammoniſts) or vpon our <hi>outward profeſſion of faigned holineſſe,</hi> (with masked Hypocrites:) but vpon the <hi>rocky faundation of thy Chriſt and his ſacred truth,</hi> both by hearing and practizing: that no <hi>raine of worldly proſperity,</hi> nor <hi>ſtormes of aduerſity, windes of haereticall perſwaſions,</hi> or <hi>violent flouds of perſecutions,</hi> ouerthrow this our ſpirituall building: but that it may ſtand faſt like mount Sion till (this houſe of our earthly tabernacle being diſſolued) wee haue a building giuen vs of thee, an houſe not made with hands but eternall in the Heauens.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:21343:42"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
